<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The chaste seraglian, or, Yolanda of Sicily a novel, in two parts / done out of French by T.H. ...</title>
            <author>Préchac, Jean de, 1647?-1720.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55662</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3204</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31911</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12273824</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12273824</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58385</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55662)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58385)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1512:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The chaste seraglian, or, Yolanda of Sicily a novel, in two parts / done out of French by T.H. ...</title>
                  <author>Préchac, Jean de, 1647?-1720.</author>
                  <author>Hayes, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 163 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Bentley and S. Magnes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXV [1685]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Illustrated added t.p.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Tho. Hayes.</note>
                  <note>"Yolanda of Sicily" (part 2) has special t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="frontispiece">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58385:1"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>The CHASTE SERAGLIAN novell.</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58385:1"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Chaſte Seraglian:</hi> OR, YOLANDA OF SICILY. A NOVEL.</p>
                  <p>IN TWO PARTS.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Done out of</hi> French <hi>by</hi> T.H. <hi>Gent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Bentley</hi> and <hi>S. Magnes,</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel-ſtreet</hi> near <hi>Covent-garden.</hi> MDCLXXXV.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58385:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58385:2"/>
                  <head>To the Honourable Sir <hi>William Kenricke</hi> BARONET.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe fam'd Gallantry of Your Family has invited this La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Addreſſes for Your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and Protection. Miſery proves often, at leaſt gains the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of Merit, and is never baro'd Refuge by the Brave and Generous: And ſince Miſery and Merit concur ſo highly in this Lady, as to make her the Object of the Compaſſion of thoſe that are the leaſt guilty of Tenderneſs, no doubt but Your Hereditary Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs will open her an Aſyle. Her Misfortunes and her Charms afford Title ſufficient for a Sanctuary; but ſhe has ſtill that of a Stranger to plead
<pb facs="tcp:58385:3"/>on her behalf. She's ſenſible, ſo much Good-nature as You are own'd to ſtand poſſeſs'd of, will not require ſo many Qualifications for a favourable Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: For all the noted Advantages of Your ſeveral Anceſtors ſeem rendez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous'd in Your Perſon, tho' in each there ſhin'd the Qualities that make a Gallant Man. She fancies the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances and Beauties of her Story to be ſuch, as to furniſh your Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, at the ſame time they move Your Pity. But having <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher'd her into Your Preſence, I'll leave her to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint You with her Caſe, and enlarge this Trouble no further than the Aſſurances of my being with the deepeſt Zeal and moſt profound Reſpect,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     <signed>Your moſt Humble and<lb/> moſt Obedient Servant,<lb/> 
                        <hi>THO. HAYES.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="novel">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58385:3"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>YOLANDA</hi> OF SICILY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SIcily</hi> is a famous Iſland in the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> at the farther end of <hi>Italy.</hi> Its Extent, the Fertility of its Soil, and the <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ecurity of its Ports, render it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut contradiction, the moſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>able of that Sea. All theſe Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ges, which ought to make it a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y Kingdom, have onely ſerv'd to <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>nder it the Prey of all the Nations <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Africa</hi> and <hi>Europe,</hi> between which <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wo Parts of the World it is ſituated <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he <hi>Greeks,</hi> the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>omans,</hi> and <hi>Saracens,</hi> made it for a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58385:4"/>long time the Stage of War. The Kings of <hi>Naples</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>Anjou,</hi> and the Kings of <hi>Aragon,</hi> did afterwards diſpute the Poſſeſſion of it with the higheſt obſtinacy: The <hi>Sicilian Veſpers</hi> rendred the latter the Maſters of this Realm, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizans of the Houſe of <hi>Anjou</hi> having been ſor the moſt part exterminated in that fatal Day, and the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Policy having ſince taken care to extinguiſh all that remain'd of that Party.</p>
                  <p>The Houſe of <hi>Cigala</hi> was one of the moſt conſiderable of thoſe which bore an affection to the <hi>French</hi> Name; but the <hi>Spaniards</hi> being peaceable Poſſeſſors of the Iſland, that Illuſtrious Family ſaw it ſelf upon the point of being deſtroy'd, when it was ſeen to riſe again by an Accident altogether extraordinary.</p>
                  <p>Some <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Corſaires having made a Deſcent into <hi>Sicily,</hi> they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away from thence ſeveral Slaves, amongſt whom was the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58385:4"/>Head of the Houſe of <hi>Cigala,</hi> with an onely Son of about ſeven or eight years of age. The Father being dead in Chains, the Son was by the <hi>Turks</hi> put into the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> where he perfected himſelf in all the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes which are taught the Youth. The vivacity of his Wit, which had gained him the good Opinion and Favour of the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained him immediately conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Employments at the Port; and his Merit made him afterwards at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the principal Charges of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire. He it was who rendred himſelf ſo Famous under the Name of Baſhaw <hi>Cigala.</hi> The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of his Extraction, and the Sentiments of a Religion which the <hi>Turks</hi> had not been able to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh in his Heart, tho' he quitted it in a very tender Age, created in him often a Deſire of returning into his own Country: But theſe Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons would not have been ſtrong enough to have made him take that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58385:5"/>Reſolution, if he had not been deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to it by an extraordinary Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</p>
                  <p>The Cuſtom of the <hi>Turks</hi> allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 'em to have ſeveral Wives, there hapned to be one amongſt thoſe of the Baſhaw who had been taken up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Coaſts of <hi>Italy,</hi> being a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Quality, and very much wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to her Religion. She reinfla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Boſom of <hi>Cigala</hi> all that had been left therein of his firſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, which made him at length reſolve to return with her into his Native Country. He landed at <hi>Meſſina,</hi> with immenſe Riches, after having eſcaped with a great deal of difficulty from the Vigilancy of the <hi>Turks.</hi> Being thus re-entred into the Religion of his Forefathers, he quickly re-united to his Family moſt of the Lands which had been alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated from it. His Riches, and the Splendour of this Life, began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive the Jealouſie of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> when that the change of Climate
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58385:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>put a period to the Days of this Great Man. He left but one Son by his Marriage; and this Son, who was called Don <hi>Bernardin,</hi> was brought up hy his Mother with all the Care imaginable. No ſooner was he out of his Infancy, than that he reſolved to court Glory in the Field of War: The emulation he had for that which his Father had acquired therein, made him follow that Noble Calling with a great deal fo Succeſs; and he would with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt have made great progreſs in that Career, if the Jealouſie of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> whom the Fathers Merit had given but too much umbrage, had not deprived him of the Means. They would have made ſure of Don <hi>Bernardin,</hi> by engaging him to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a young Lady of their Nation; but all their Practices were in vain, and Don <hi>Bernardin,</hi> who had no leſs averſion for them than his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, and who ſought to gain a conſiderable Support againſt 'em,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58385:6"/>married a <hi>Roman</hi> Princeſs of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Family of the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſins.</hi> The Grandeur of this Alliance, and the Union of Don <hi>Bernardin</hi> to a Houſe that had ever been wedded to the <hi>French</hi> Party, already gave umbrage to the <hi>Spaniards:</hi> But having diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in ſeveral Rencounters their Ill-will, and remarked their Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation contrary to his Family, he did not doubt but that the ſame Reaſons would make 'em ſeek out the Means of ruining it a ſecond time; and knowing by experience how dangerous it is to incur the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation of his Maſters, he reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to avoid the Occaſions of giving them any Jealouſie in vain, and to withdraw into a Country-houſe, far from all Commerce, where he ſpent ſome Years, waiting till Time ſhould furniſh him with the Occaſions of ſhewing 'em his Reſentment. The Power of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weakned at that time by the happy Succeſs of the Arms of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58385:6"/>
                     <hi>French,</hi> Don <hi>Bernardin</hi> judg'd that this might give Occaſion to ſome Motion in the Dominions which the King of <hi>Spain</hi> poſſeſſes in <hi>Intaly:</hi> He was not miſtaken in his Conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures. The Kingdom of <hi>Naples</hi> being revolted, and the Malecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents having called in the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> to aſſure themſelves of a Head, Don <hi>Bernadin</hi> thought that time proper for the Deſigns he had medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated. He took Meaſures with that Duke, and ſet Cabals on foot in the Iſland. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> had ſome ſuſpicion of theſe Practices, and tho' all his Cabals were not come to their knowledge, they diſcover'd enough of 'em to take the Reſolution of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying <hi>Cigala.</hi> Cardinal <hi>Trivulce</hi> being then Vice Roy of <hi>Sicily,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived order from <hi>Spain</hi> to take him into Cuſtody; and tho' this Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe was ſomewhat difficult, this Cardinal, who was one of the moſt able Politicians of his time, executed it with ſo much cunning, that Don
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58385:7"/>
                     <hi>Bernardin</hi> was taken, and carried to the Caſtle of <hi>S. Sauveur;</hi> the Vice-Roy having had the Precaution to ſend out of the way part of <hi>Cigala's</hi> Friends, to engage others in his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, and to amuſe' em all, by aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring 'em, that the Court procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed onely in that manner to take away all pretext from the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> from publiſhing in <hi>Naples,</hi> as he did, That he had a great Party in <hi>Sicily,</hi> and that all the Kingdom would ſuddenly declare infavour of him. When Don <hi>Bernardin</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into Cuſtody, he had an onely Daughter of about five or ſix Years of age, called <hi>Yolanda:</hi> The Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> having had the misfortune of falling into the Hands of the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards,</hi> was carried into <hi>Spain;</hi> and the Diſorders of <hi>Naples</hi> were quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ended by ſevere Puniſhments. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> having no more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to fear any Riſing or Revolt in <hi>Sicily,</hi> the Friends of the Houſe of <hi>Cigala</hi> were in hopes that Don <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardin</hi>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:58385:7"/>would be ſet at liberty; but they expected it in vain.</p>
                  <p>The Senate of <hi>Meſſina,</hi> that inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſed it ſelf in the Preſervation of a Man with whoſe Merit they were ſo well acquainted, and who beſides judged, that a perpetual Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, upon meer Suſpicions, would be of a dangerous Example to the moſt Conſiderable Perſons of the Kingdom, caus'd his Releaſment to be demanded of the King of <hi>Spain:</hi> But very far from obtaining this Requeſt, their preſſing Solicitations did ſo exaſperate the Council, and the King took it ſo ill that the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſhould make the Buſineſs of a Private Perſon its own, that it was reſolved from that time to ſuppreſs its, Authority. And indeed all the Governours, who have been ſince ſent to <hi>Meſſina,</hi> have had ſecret <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moires</hi> to endeavour the Execution of this Deſign. This is the true beginning and ſource of the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes which have oppreſſed that.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58385:8"/>City in theſe latter Times. Don <hi>Bernardin</hi> was ſtill ſtrictly kept in Priſon: His beſt Friends adviſed him to diſſemble his Reſentment, and to comply with Time by making great Submiſſions to the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> A Counſel ſo oppoſite to his natural. Inclination, and the grandeur of a Courage which knew not how to bend, put him at firſt to as much pain as his Impriſonment, not being able to promiſe what he perceived it would be difficult for him to keep, but in ſhort, this Advice was too healing to be neglected, and he was forced to comply with it, after a great many Conflicts. The Duke of <hi>Salvonella,</hi> who ſucceeded Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Trivulce</hi> in the Vice-Roy ſhip of <hi>Sicily,</hi> and whom the Friends of Don <hi>Bernardin</hi> had engaged in his Intereſts, was overjoyed to ſee him in Sentiments conformable to their Counſels: He wrote into <hi>Spain</hi> in favour of this Priſoner, and hopes were given him that regard ſhould
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58385:8"/>be had to his Remonſtranees. But whether that there ſtill remained ſome Miſtruſt in the Minds of the Miniſters, or that he had had ſecret Enemies who oppoſed his Releaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he remained ſtill a Priſoner.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> commonly ſeek to make ſure of the Fidelity of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies the moſt Conſiderable in the States ſubject to their Government; and have not found a more aſſured Means of bringing that about, than that of having brought up at <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid</hi> Children of the Higheſt Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, whom they detain at Court as Hoſtages of their Parents Servitude: They engage 'em afterwards in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages with <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ladies, who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten bring no other Portion into thoſe Families than the Hopes alone of a Government ſuitable to their Extraction. The Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> and Don <hi>Auguſtin Gregorio,</hi> both of 'em <hi>Meſſineſes,</hi> were then at <hi>Madrid,</hi> in quality of <hi>Meninos</hi> or Children of Honour to the King of <hi>Spain.</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:58385:9"/>The Duke of <hi>Salmonetta,</hi> who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got nothing that might uſefully ſerve Don <hi>Bernardin,</hi> adviſed him to ſend into <hi>Spain Yolanda</hi> his onely Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to be brought up there near the Queen: and that this Mark of Truſt might both promote his Liberty, and afterwards procure him ſeveral other Favours Don <hi>Bernardin</hi> reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a long while the Reaſons of the Vice-Roy; the Tenderneſs he had for his Daughter, was a great Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacle to this Separation. But what would he not have don, to ſee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf free after ſo long an Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? He ſuffered himſelf to be perſuaded, and conſented that the Dutcheſs of <hi>Salmonetta,</hi> who was returning into <hi>Spain,</hi> ſhould take <hi>Yolanda</hi> with her thither. This young Lady was about ten years of age; and as ſhe had an extreme re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnance to part from her Parents, who had already inſpired into her the Sentiments of their Family a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> ſhe did not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58385:9"/>love 'em at all. Thus was ſhe very loth to go this Voyage; yet they knew ſo well how to take advantage of the weakneſs of her Infancy, that ſhe ſuffered her felf at length to be conducted to <hi>Madrid,</hi> where ſhe was received into the number of the Queens Maids of Honour, or <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas de Palacio.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After ſuch a Sacrifice, Don <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardin</hi> thought he might with right preſs the Court to grant him his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. He made new Inſtances, and employed all his Friends, without obtaining any thing more than Words, in which he could not put any confidence, becauſe they had fail'd him already ſeveral times. He was beſides afraid, that the Council of <hi>Spain</hi> had reſolved upon his Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine. Certain it is, that he died in a ſhort while after in the Priſon, and without its ever yet being fully known if his Death were Natural. However, as on theſe occaſions Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are ever inclined to believe the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58385:10"/>worſt, no Body but ſuſpected they had haſtned his Days; and all the Nobility of <hi>Meſſina</hi> had in ſuch ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence ſo barbarous an Action, that ſince that time they have ever look'd upon the <hi>Spaniards</hi> as down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Enemies, who cannot endure thoſe who are Eminent, either for their Quality, or their Merit. The Wife of Don <hi>Bernardin</hi> died in a ſhort while after. Thus <hi>Yolanda</hi> finding herſelf an Orphan at twelve Years of age, the Queen, who bore her a tender Love, endeavoured to comfort her with fair Promiſes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yolanda</hi> ſometimes ſaw the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta</hi> and Don <hi>Auguſt in Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorio.</hi> Theſe two young Cavaliers, who ſpoke to her without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, acquainted her with the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors which ran of her Fathers Death being haſtned, and the Indignation which all the Nobility of <hi>Meſſina</hi> had conceived upon that account. As ſhe had a great deal of Wit, and more Sagacity than Maidens of that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58385:10"/>Age uſually have, this News did ſo highly augment her Averſion to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> that ſhe could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear ſhewing it upon occaſion. She durſt not however give it vent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the World; but when ſhe found her ſelf alone with the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta</hi> and D. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> ſhe abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her ſelf to all her Griefs, and ſpoke no leſs than of revenging the Death of her Father, and of giving her ſelf afterwards for a Reward to him who ſhould free her Country from the Government of the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards.</hi> They both partook with her in her Reſentment; but the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> who was the oldeſt of the two, aſſured her, That he ſhould eſteem himſelf very happy, if he could contribute to her Revenge; and that he would periſh with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in ſo glorious a Deſign. <hi>Yo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landa</hi> took this very kindly at his Hands, and deſired him to be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of his Engagement. This Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation ended by Aſſurances of a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58385:11"/>great deal of Acknowledgement in <hi>Yolanda,</hi> and of an eternal Devotion on the part of the Prince of <hi>Eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letta.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Such like Entertainments created in 'em a great Eſteem for one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and as there is no great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from this Sentiment to Love, the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta</hi> found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in a ſhort while paſſionately en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amour'd of <hi>Yolanda.</hi> She was at fourteen years of age the moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Beauty of all <hi>Spain:</hi> She had a delicate and advantageous Shape; her Complexion was of a ſurpriſing White and Incarnation; never was there finer Eyes than hers; they were full, black, and paſſionate to ſuch a point, as it was impoſſible to look upon 'em without being filled with Wonder and Adoration; her Noſe was well proportioned, her Mouth ſomewhat large, but ſet off with Lips of a wonderful Colour; her Teeth perfectly fine, the turn of her Face accompliſhed, her Neck
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58385:11"/>well formed for her Age; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all this, the Qualities of her Mind much ſurpaſſing thoſe of her beautiful Body. The Queen was ſo ſatisfied with her Perſon, and had ſo much Kindneſs for her, that ſhe had ſeveral times refuſed to her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations the Permiſſion for her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to <hi>Meſſina,</hi> and had declared to them, That ſhe did not in the leaſt deſign to deprive her ſelf ſo ſoon of ſo lovely a Perſon. And that ſhe Might ſuffer this kind of Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment with the leſs impatience, ſhe was allowed little Liberties, which are not uſed to be granted to the Maids of Honour. The young Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> and Don <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin Gregorio,</hi> were ſometimes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to viſt her, becauſe they were of the ſame Country. The firſt found his Paſſion to augment every day: Yet as it is a Crime in <hi>Spain</hi> to ſpeak of Love to one of the Queens Maids of Honour, and that to be baniſh'd away from thence is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58385:12"/>inevitable, if that one be diſcovered, every time that the Prince called to mind, that he could not give any Tokens of his Paſſion to <hi>Yolanda,</hi> without expoſing himſelf to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeparated from her, he had no longer the power to ſpeak. This Conſideration would perhaps for a long while have detained him in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, if Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> had not one day made known to him, by his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſes, that <hi>Yolanda</hi> ſeem'd to him ſo charming, that he began to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain for her ſomething more ſtrong than Friendſhip. The Prince very much ſurpris'd at this Account, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented himſelf at that time with telling his Friend, That it was very dangerous for him to confide in any other leſs diſcreet Friend the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments he had for <hi>Yolanda,</hi> deſiring him very earneſtly to be reſerved upon that Point, for fear they ſhould be both forbid to ſee her. Don <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin</hi> yielded to theſe Reaſons, and promiſed to follow his Counſels.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58385:12"/>The Prince being afraid that his Rival ſpeaking firſt, might eſtabliſh himſelf in the Heart of <hi>Yolanda,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to declare to her his Paſſion, whenever he met with her alone.</p>
                  <p>The Deſign which ſet him on to ſeek for that Occaſion, made his Looks ſeem to be in ſome perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; which <hi>Yolanda</hi> perceiving, ſhe asked him the Cauſe thereof. The Prince, who would never have da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to have told her his Sentiments for her, became more bold thro' the Curioſity ſhe had ſhewed, and made her Anſwer, <hi>That one of his Friends, who was paſſionately in love with one of the Queens Maids of Honour, had hapned to ſpeak of his Paſſion to her who had produced it; that ſhe had threatned to give the Queen notice thereof; and that his Friend was in the greateſt Conſternation imaginable, fearing to be ſeparated from her he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; That he deſired her to tell him if ſhe approved of ſuch violent Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in a Beautiful Perſon, for whom
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58385:13"/>his Friend had a Paſſion full of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, which he explain'd, it being no longer in his power to conceal it. Yo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landa,</hi> without making him any An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to his Queſtion, deſired him to tell her that Ladies Name. The Prince, pretending not to name it out of diſcretion for his Friend, drew the Pourtraict of <hi>Yolanda,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by made known to her his Paſſion. As ſhe had a great deal of Wit, ſhe eaſily knew what he had a mind to give her to underſtand: <hi>I am very glad,</hi> ſaid ſhe to him, ſomething diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order'd, <hi>that you your ſelf have taught me before-hand what my Duty is: I ſhould be afraid you might have an ill Opinion of me, if I did not follow your Counſels, by complaining to the Queen of your Boldneſs.</hi> A troubleſom Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-Governeſs, coming in at that time, deprived them of the means of continuing that Converſation. The Prince before he parted told her in the <hi>Sicilian</hi> Tongue, That having devoted himſelf entirely to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58385:13"/>her Service, he deſired her to be mindful that ſhe could not ſacrifice him, without loſing the Man who endeavoured to revenge her. But the Air wherewith ſhe left him, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given him to underſtand, that ſhe was not diſpleaſed at his Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he withdrew very much ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with having diſcovered to her a Secret which he had found ſo pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to conceal from her.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yolanda,</hi> who had never felt any other Deſire than that of being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged, and who was not yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with Love, was very much ſurpriſed at what ſhe had juſt learnt from the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> and making Reflection upon all the Care and Pains he had taken to pleaſe her, ſhe judged that his Paſſion muſt of neceſſity be very violent. At firſt the auſterity of her Virtue made her repent the having ſhewed ſo little Anger at their parting; but what ſhe owed her Father, coming to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it ſelf to her Imagination, ſhe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58385:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>reſolved not to diſcourage that Prince. Perhaps ſhe did to ſatisfie her Inclination, what ſhe thought ſhe afforded to the Hopes of being revenged.</p>
                  <p>The Prince on his ſide courted the Occaſions of diſcourſing her, that he might the more clearly make her explain her Mind: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, fearing he could not be alone with her, he asked her in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Don <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> if the Anger of her Companion did ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue. <hi>Yolanda,</hi> who underſtood his Thoughts, made him anſwer, That the Perſon had upon her deſire par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned the Offence that had been done her; nay, that ſhe allowed his Friend to love her, upon condition he would never tell it her again. Don <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> who underſtood no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of this Language, was very impatient to be alone with his Friend, to inform himſelf of the Matter; and having preſſed him to acquaint him with the Buſineſs, the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58385:14"/>Prince was obliged to tell him, That one of the Maids of Honour would have complained to the Queen, for that her Lover had entertained her with ſome Amorous Diſcourſes; and that <hi>Yolanda</hi> had had the Goodneſs to hinder her from ſo doing. <hi>I am overjoyed,</hi> ſaid Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, <hi>that ſhe is ſo indulgent; and I mean to morrow to ſpeak to her of my Paſſion. Have a care of what you do,</hi> replied the Prince; <hi>People do not always practiſe the Counſels they give: and tho'</hi> Yolanda <hi>has blamed the Injuſtice of her Companion, I know not what ſhe would do if ſhe were in her Place.</hi> Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> was a long while before he came to any Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination; but his Love having got the maſtery over all his Reaſonings, he reſolved to ſpeak. He was youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than his Friend: His Birth was not indeed ſo conſiderable, but his Beauty was extraordinary; and the great Opinion he had of his good Meen, made him believe he ſhould
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58385:15"/>be heard. Having declared his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to the Prince, who could never divert him from it, he went all alone to ſee <hi>Yolanda.</hi> After ſome moments of Converſation, he owned to her very ingenuouſly, That he found himſelf very much puzled to begin to her a Diſcourſe, which he had reſolved to entertain her with. <hi>Yolanda,</hi> thinking of nothing leſs than of what Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> meant to tell her, preſſed him to ſpeak, Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> having exacted that ſhe ſhould not be angry, declared to her at length his being in love with her. <hi>Yolanda</hi> not having ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly converſed with Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> as with the Prince, yet could not forbear bluſhing a little; however, being quickly recollected, ſhe turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the thing into Raillery, and laugh'd at him for having uſed ſo much Ceremony to tell her ſo tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial a Matter. They parted in a ſhort while after.</p>
                  <p>The Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta</hi> being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58385:15"/>the greateſt impatience imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to know the Succeſs of that Viſit, began to grow uneaſie; when Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> told him all that had paſſed. On the morrow they went both together to ſee her; and the Prince deſiring to pry into the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timent of <hi>Yolanda</hi> for Don <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> told her, after a rallying manner. That Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> was very much concerned to tell her that he loved her, and that he took it very ill ſhe did not take it ſeriouſly. <hi>You are too obliging to your Friends,</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Yolanda; think onely of giving good Counſels to him whom we ſpoke of laſt of all: You will have buſineſs enough, without concerning your ſelf in the Affairs of Don</hi> Auguſtin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yolanda</hi> ſpent ſome Months long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in this manner, not troubling her ſelf about the Paſſion of Don <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> and taking a ſecret delight in that of the Prince. Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> being diſcouraged by finding her al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways inſenſible, thought of her no
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58385:16"/>more. The Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied himſelf ſtill more and more to pleaſe her; ſhe liſtned to him in the beginning, thinking ſhe might do it without hazarding any thing of her own, and without any Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments eſcaping from her againſt her will. Her Confidence was not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well founded: As all yields to any real Love, and that it is a hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to think ones ſelf tenderly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd, without taking a particular Intereſt in People; <hi>Yolanda</hi> was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd upon by the Addreſſes of the Prince, and ſoon perceived there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by how dangerous it is to allow of the Paſſion of a well-bred Man, when a Woman means not to engage her Heart. The Prince having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of this happy Change, by the Diſcourſes and good Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his Miſtreſs, abandoned himſelf before her to ſuch Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports as made her acquainted with the exceſs of his Love.</p>
                  <p>The Satisfaction of the two Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58385:16"/>was too viſible, and the pleaſure they took in being together, made them ſeek with too much care the Occaſions of diſcourſing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in a Court where People live with ſo much circumſpection. In fine, the Prince was forbid ſeeing her. This Prohibition, which ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly afflicted him, did more promote his Affairs, than long Services could have done: For <hi>Yolanda</hi> being irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated by this Order, which they found ſo much the more Tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, in that it came from People whom ſhe reſpected againſt her will, and whom ſhe ever look'd upon as the Perſecutors and Diſturbers of her Family, and of many others of that ancient and moſt renowned Kingdom of <hi>Sicily,</hi> this made her reſolve to love him all her Life with an inſeparable Love, in ſpite of all the Obſtacles and Impediments that might be brought to hinder her ſo doing.</p>
                  <p>In the mean while, all the Court
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58385:17"/>talk'd and diſcours'd daily of this Beauty, extolled even to the firſt Rank above all others. Her Birth was alſo very well known by all the Nobility; and tho' ſhe had a vaſt Eſtate in the Kingdom of <hi>Sicily,</hi> the common Rumour made it much more than it really was. Several Grandees of <hi>Spain</hi> thought of her, as of one of the moſt conſiderable Matches of that Illuſtrious and Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Court: And one of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Miniſters had ſeveral times employed his Credit with the Queen to have her married to the Marquis of <hi>Caſtel-Rodrigo,</hi> who was a Perſon of much Merit and high Quality, and a great Favourite of the Kings; but who, on the other ſide, had but a very ſmall ſhare in the Bleſſings of Fortune.</p>
                  <p>The Marchioneſs of <hi>Villa Franca,</hi> Lady of Honour to the Queen, who was very much beloved in the Court for her fine Qualities, had had the ſame thoughts for the Duke of <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandina</hi>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:58385:17"/>her Son, and had alſo ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken thereof to the Queen: But her Majeſty not being able to part with a Perſon ſhe loved from her very Heart, ſtill deferred coming to a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination. The Marchioneſs's Place obliging her to be at at Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, ſhe took advantage of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency of ſeeing <hi>Yolanda</hi> every Hour, did her a thouſand Kindneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. And that young Perſon not knowing whither all theſe Careſſes tended, made ſuch Returns as ſpoke a great deal of Acknowledgement. This made the Marchioneſs conceive ſuch good hopes for the Succeſs of her Sons Marriage, that ſhe ſpoke thereof one day, as of an Affair without difficulty, to a Lady of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cily</hi> who had been recommended to her, and who at that time ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſome Pretenſions at the Court. This <hi>Sicilian</hi> extolled extremely the Quality and Riches of the Houſe of <hi>Cigala;</hi> and the Marchioneſs deſir'd her earneſtly to keep the Buſineſs
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58385:18"/>ſecret. Nevertheleſs, as moſt of the <hi>Sicilians</hi> do naturally hate the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> as ſoon as the Counteſs of <hi>Caſtelmara</hi> (ſo is the Ladies Name) found the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> ſhe acquainted him with all the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe ſhe had had with the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs of <hi>Villa-Franca,</hi> ſhewing too a great deal of Grief, in that a <hi>Spaniard</hi> carried away the richeſt Heireſs of her Country.</p>
                  <p>The Prince, who had already heard talk confuſedly of <hi>Caſtel-Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drigo</hi>'s Pretenſion, was cruelly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm'd to hear moreover of the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of the Marchioneſs of <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la-Franca.</hi> Two days after, the Counteſs of <hi>Caſtelmara</hi> told him, That the Marchioneſs had preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her to <hi>Yolanda,</hi> and that ſhe had deſired her to go ſee her often, and inſinuate into her, That the Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of the Duke of <hi>Fernandina</hi> would be more to her advantage, than all thoſe that could be propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to her. <hi>And what Anſwer did
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58385:18"/>you make her?</hi> interrupted the Prince. <hi>I promiſed to take my time to ſpeak to her thereof,</hi> replied the Counteſs. <hi>Is this then,</hi> continued he, <hi>the Grief which you told me you had to ſee</hi> Yo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landa <hi>carried away by a</hi> Spaniard? <hi>And can you diſapprove of a thing which you mean to be the Mediatrix in?</hi> The Counteſs finding more Heat in this Diſcourſe of the Prince, than could well proceed from he In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt alone of his Nation, <hi>I have already told you my Thoughts,</hi> added ſhe; <hi>but having occaſion for the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs, I could not refuſe her what ſhe has exacted from me: However, if you love</hi> Yolanda, <hi>as it ſeems to me you do by your Diſcourſes, be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that I know how to ſet the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference I ought between you and a</hi> Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard. The Prince gave her a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand thanks, and engaged her, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Converſation was at an end, to give a Letter from him to <hi>Yolanda,</hi> which he withdrew to write ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:58385:19"/>
                  <p> The Counteſs, who was obliged to improve the Marchioneſs's Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, upon the account of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns which had brought her to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid,</hi> began to repent of her Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when that the Prince return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his Letter; and finding her irreſolved, he deſired her anew, with ſo much earneſtneſs, that ſhe promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him at length to keep with him her Word: Whereupon ſhe ſought out the Expedients of delivering it to <hi>Yolanda</hi> after ſuch a manner as might never expoſe her to the being diſcovered, and without <hi>Yolanda</hi>'s perceiving ſhe had taken upon her the Commiſſion. This ſeem'd ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing difficult; yet as there be few Difficulties of that nature, but which the Cunning of a Woman does ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount, when ſhe applies her Mind to the thing, the Counteſs, after having thought of it for ſome time, bethought her ſelf of making a Pac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet of ſeveral Letters which ſhe had newly received from <hi>Sicily,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58385:19"/>which ſhe put that from the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> and having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven this Pacquet to one of her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, with order to pretend he had newly fetch'd it from the Poſt-houſe, and to bring it to her to the Palace, in the Apartment of the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Villa-Franca.</hi> The Counteſs having opened her Pacquet in the preſence of the Marchioneſs and <hi>Yo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landa,</hi> gave her the Princes, pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not to know from whom it was, becauſe ſhe had not yet read her own. The Marchioneſs withdrew, out of diſcretion, to give them time to read their Letters, being perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that her Friend would effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do her Devoirs, when ſhe found an opportunity of ſpeaking in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Duke of <hi>Fernandina.</hi> She was not miſtaken; for the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs not being willing to expoſe <hi>Yo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landa</hi> to the diſorder which ſhe ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily foreſaw the reading of her Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Letter would create in her, took that time to extol to her the great
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58385:20"/>Advantages of the Alliance of the Duke of <hi>Fernandina,</hi> who was then General of the Gallies of <hi>Naples,</hi> nay, and was in hopes, by the Credit of his Mother, to ſucceed Don <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro d' Aragon</hi> in the Viceroy-ſhip of that Kingdom. The Marchioneſs being returned into her Chamber, was overjoyed to find 'em engaged in this Converſation, and would have gone back, not to interrupt it, pretending not to have taken notice thereof: But <hi>Yolanda</hi> having percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved her, took occaſion to follow her, and ſo free her ſelf from the troubleſom Converſation of the Counteſs.</p>
                  <p>As ſoon as <hi>Yolanda</hi> found her ſelf alone, ſhe was impatient to read her Letter, wherein ſhe saw, with a great deal of ſurpriſe, the Name of the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta;</hi> and not being able to comprehend by what hazard this Letter had come thro' the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs's Hands, whom ſhe thought ſo oppoſite to the Intereſts of her Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58385:20"/>her Paſſion made her fear he might have been ſent back into <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cily:</hi> But theſe Diſquiets were at an end, when that reading the Letter, ſhe found therein theſe Words.</p>
                  <q>BEing aſſured of your Heart, I did not believe I could ever have fallen under any ſenſible Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune: Nevertheleſs, I find my ſelf the moſt miſerable of all Men. I am for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to ſee you, and I juſt now learn the fatal News of the Marriage to which they mean to force you. I trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for fear you ſhould at length yield to the Artifices of thoſe who take over you ſo unjuſt an Authority. Give 'em all the Reaſons which may divert them from this Deſign, and if it be poſſible, take 'em all from your Paſſion: If it be too weak, remember at leaſt what you are owing to your Revenge, and never doubt of the Fidelity of the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:58385:21"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>Yolanda</hi> was very glad to have ſeen by this Letter that her Lover was in the Sentiments ſhe deſired he might have, tho' the delicacy of her Paſſion found it ſelf ſomewhat wounded by the Princes Diſtruſts; but not daring to truſt any Body, being uncertain if the Counteſs knew of their Correſpondence, ſhe bethought herſelf at length of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Artifice, and reſolved to hazard an Anſwer by the ſame way. On the morrow ſhe told the Counteſs, That the Letter ſhe had delivered her was from the Prince of <hi>Eſcalet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi>'s Siſter, and then deſired her to deliver the Anſwer to her Brother, that he might ſend it to <hi>Sicily</hi> in his Pacquet. The Counteſs admiring the Induſtry of <hi>Yolanda,</hi> ſeemed to believe her in good earneſt, and charg'd her ſelf with this Letter, which ſhe delivered faithfully to the Prince, wherein was written,</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:58385:21"/> 
                     <hi>I</hi> Know not why I am ſo ſenſible to the Teſtimonies of your Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, in a time you let me ſee you entertain ſuch injurious Diſtruſts. I ſhould hardly pardon you 'em, if I did not look upon 'em as Effects of your Paſſion. True it is, that I have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd me conſiderable Matches: But can you believe, that having a Father to revenge, and having known you, I can confide in any other the Secret of my Vengeance, after having abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to you that of my Love? No, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver doubt in the leaſt, and be perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that nothing but Death can raviſh from you, your <hi>Yolanda.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>The Prince was filled with all the Joy imaginable at the reading of ſo tender a Letter; but having the Indiſcretion of moſt young People, and believing that his Happineſs would not be compleat if ſome other had not the knowledge of it, he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted his Secret to Don <hi>Auguſtin
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58385:22"/>Gregorio,</hi> and ſhewed him the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had newly received, well knowing he loved another Lady, and no longer thought of <hi>Yolanda.</hi> Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> diſſembling his true Sentiments, by a piece of Cunning above his Age, tho' moſt common to People of his Country, teſtified a great deal of Joy for the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Friend; but indeed the Paſſion he had had for <hi>Yolanda</hi> being revived at the reading of this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he reſolved to make his Addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to her anew. The ſmall hopes he had had of rendring her ſenſible, had diſcouraged him from proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that Amour; but being unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd by the Experience of his Friend, and having found that no Woman is Proof againſt a very real Paſſion, and a long Perſeverance, he repented a thouſand times his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engaging himſelf ſo eaſily, and took a ſtrong Reſolution of putting all in practice to gain a Heart which he fancied he had loſt thro' his impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58385:22"/>As he was perfectly handſom, and well made, and that it is rare to ſee in <hi>Spain</hi> young men of ſo great a Beauty, he attracted upon him the Eyes of all the Ladies: Nay, and he had obſerved too, that one of thoſe of the Palace, a little ſuperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated, whoſe Name I will conceal under that of Donna <hi>Ignes,</hi> affected to do him Favours which are not commonly done to indifferent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Love, which is ingenious, inſpired him with the Deſign to make uſe of the Miniſtry of this Woman, for the giving <hi>Yolanda</hi> to underſtand the Sentiments he had for her; and the Facilities he had already met with in another, made him hope he ſhould eaſily bring Donna <hi>Ignes</hi> into his Intereſt, ſince ſhe ſhewed him ſo much Good-will.</p>
                  <p>What ſelf-love ſoever there might be in this thought, the Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces let him ſee that he was not mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, and Donna <hi>Ignes</hi> did not ſuffer him long to make her Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58385:23"/>with Impunity. She endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on her ſide to embarque Don <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin,</hi> and they were quickly in a perfect good Intelligence. She was ſo ſatisfied with having at her Age a Lover with ſo good a Meen, and loved him with ſo much traſport, that it was no longer in the power of Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> to ſpeak to any Woman, without giving Jealouſie to Donna <hi>Ignes;</hi> and far from daring to make her the Confident of his Paſſion for <hi>Yolanda,</hi> he was obliged to conceal it from her with more care than from his Rival. This gave him extreme diſquiets; and no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er being able to continue feigning a Paſſion which he did not feel, he ſought out for a Pretext to break off ſo weariſom a Commerce; when that Donna <hi>Ignes,</hi> who on her ſide onely thought to make ſure of a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo worthy of being beloved, and who was afraid a young Perſon might rob her of her Conqueſt, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to him the putting himſelf
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:58385:23"/>into Womans Clothes, and to go with her into the Palace, where ſhe would make him paſs for her Niece, promiſing to diſguiſe him ſo well, that he ſhould never be known again, and aſſuring him, for to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage him to it, that he ſhould par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take in all the Pleaſures of the Maids of Honour, and in all the ſecret Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſements of the Palace.</p>
                  <p>Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> overjoy'd at a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition which ſo ſtrongly flatter'd his Paſſion for <hi>Yolanda,</hi> redoubled his feigned Addreſſes to <hi>Ignes;</hi> and making a ſhew of not being able to refuſe any thing to his Love, he conſented to all ſhe deſired. Having afterwards given out, that he was going to ſee one of his Friends, he entred by Night ſo well <hi>traveſtied</hi> into the Palace, that no body doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but that it was the Niece of Don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na <hi>Ignes,</hi> newly arrived from <hi>Sevil,</hi> as that pretended Vertuous Lady told all he was. Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſo well maintained his Perſonage by
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:58385:24"/>his Beauty, and counterfeited with ſo good a grace the Innocence and Modeſty of a Lady who begins to appear at Court, that he deceived all the World.</p>
                  <p>As Beautiful Perſons have a ſecret Jealouſie againſt all thoſe who may diſpute with 'em that Advantage, and that a fair young Lady is rarely ſeen to come to Court, without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring the Envy of all the Ladies who pretend to the being handſom; <hi>Yolanda,</hi> who had heard talk with admiration of the Beauty of this young Lady, went to Donna <hi>Ignes</hi> Apartment, to know if the Renown which augments every thing, did Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to the Niece of that Lady; and finding her more beautiful than ſhe had been deſcribed to her, (perhaps at the Emotion which appeared in the Face of Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> at the ſight of <hi>Yolanda</hi>) ſhe let her know how overjoy'd ſhe ſhould be to contract a Friendſhip with ſo lovely a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Donna <hi>Ignes</hi> could not bear
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58385:24"/>without a great deal of pain all theſe little Engagements, covering her Jealouſie with the fear ſhe had of her Lover's being diſcovered: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, not to make him too uneaſie, ſhe could not deny him the taking him along with her to <hi>Yolanda</hi>'s Lodgings, under the pretext of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her a Viſit; but ſhe never left him, and gave not time to the amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> to diſcover him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to <hi>Yolanda.</hi> This Conſtraint augmenting his Impatience, he could no longer ſupport the violence of a Paſſion which became every day more ſtrong than other, by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of <hi>Yolanda.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>One day that Donna <hi>Ignes</hi> was employed about the Queen, he took that time to enter into <hi>Yolanda's</hi> Lodgings, and having found her alone, he ſpoke to her in the <hi>Sici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> Tongue, and made himſelf known to her, exaggerating to her his Love, with Words the moſt ſoft and tender imaginable. <hi>Yolanda</hi> was
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58385:25"/>in ſo great a ſurpriſe to ſee Don <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin</hi> in ſuch a poſture, that ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained for ſome time without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him any Anſwer; nut finding her ſelf offended at his Liberty, her Indignation prevailed over all her Motions, and ſhe was going to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain to the Queen, and inform her of his Diſguiſe, for fear People ſhould believe ſhe had any ſhare therein; when that Don <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> who had Wit, and knew that Curioſity is the weak ſide of all Women, told her, to ſtay her, that Donna <hi>Ignes</hi> had a much greater part in what he did, than he himſelf. This Artifice of his had the Succeſs ſuitable to his Expectations; for <hi>Yolanda</hi> was ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to know the Intrigues of a Woman ſhe had ever looked upon as hypocritically Vertuous, tho' al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſet as an Example to the Maids of Honour, that ſhe almoſt forgot her Anger.</p>
                  <p>Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> acquainted her with all ſhe deſired to know; and ſhe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:58385:25"/>pardoned him, upon condition he would ſee her no more. In this Converſation <hi>Yolanda</hi> ſpoke to him after ſuch a manner, as deprived him of all Hopes from thence forward; and ſetting before his Eyes his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery in this Action to his Friend, ſhe ſaw in him ſo much remorſe, that ſhe did not think ſhe ran any riſque, by ordering him to tell the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> That ſhe would ever be faithful to him.</p>
                  <p>This Converſation having laſted ſomething too long, Donna <hi>Ignes</hi> was returned to her Apartment, and not finding Don <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> ſhe ſought him out on all ſides, and ſurpriſed him at length in <hi>Yolanda</hi>'s Lodgings. The diſorder her preſence put thoſe two young perſons in, making her judge that they were of intelligence, ſhe could hardly forbear burſting out immediately into a fury: She diſſembled her Jealouſie, took back with her her pretended Niece, and as ſoon as they were alone, charged
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:58385:26"/>him to ſome purpoſe with injurious Language. Don <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> wearied out with the Tyranny of this Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and having no more hopes as to <hi>Yolanda,</hi> he began to grow weary of his Diſguiſe, and to ſhew a great deal of uneaſineſs. Donna <hi>Ignes,</hi> who obſerved him with care, and no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er finding in him his firſt Tranſports, whether feigned or real, was ſo ſtrangely concerned, that ſhe grew diſtracted; ſhe committed a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Extravagancies in the Palace, nay, and afterwards went and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to the Queen of the little Fervency of her Lover. People ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily perceived that her Brains were crack'd; and as ſhe confounded in her Diſcourſes her Lover with her Niece, and Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> with her faithleſs Gallant, the Queen had the Curioſity to dive into this Affair; and having ſent for that pretended Niece, Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> fell into ſo great a confuſion at the extravagant Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſes of diſtracted <hi>Ignes,</hi> that he
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58385:26"/>was eaſily known to be whom he really was. The Queen being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely offended at ſuch a piece of Boldneſs, had him immediately ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into Cuſtody, with deſign to puniſh him ſeverely. Poor <hi>Ignes</hi> was confined, and gave occaſion to the Rumour which ran over all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> at that time, That a Woman of Quality in <hi>Spain</hi> was become mad thro' Jealouſie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yolanda</hi> having heard talk of this unhappy Adventure, was under cruel Diſquiets, for fear of being brought into it; and as this was of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Conſequence for her, eſpecially in a Country where People are very ſuſceptible of Impreſſions diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous to Women, ſhe carefully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired into all the Circumſtances of this Affair, but was ſo happy as not to be named.</p>
                  <p>The Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> who had already repented himſelf more than once of his having ſhewed his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Don <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> ſuſpected that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:58385:27"/>
                     <hi>Yolanda</hi> had more ſhare in this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe than <hi>Ignes,</hi> and the Jealouſie of this latter confirmed him in his Errour. The Queen in the mean while was very much irritated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Don <hi>Auguſtin;</hi> yet as a Crime of Love does ever meet with Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zans, ſo many ſeveral Perſons em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd their Credit in his Favour, that they obtained at length his Pardon of the Queen, upon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, however, that he ſhould be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried back to <hi>Meſſina,</hi> in the ſame Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture he had been ſurpriſed in, in the Palace; and that he ſhould be kept a Month in the Caſtle of <hi>S. Sauveur,</hi> ſtill in the Garb of a Woman; her Majeſty being reſolved to puniſh him with the ſhame that this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe would bring upon him in his own Country. His Friends having had leave to ſee him before his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta</hi> went immediately to him, and Don <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin</hi> ſeeing him come in, embraced him with all the Teſtimonies of a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58385:27"/>real Friendſhip: He owned to him ſincerely all that had paſſed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out concealing from him, that his Paſſion for <hi>Yolanda</hi> had engaged him to feign a Love to <hi>Ignes;</hi> but that he had found her ſo far from ever liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to any other Paſſion than that of the P. of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> that deſpair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of being ever able to make her change her Sentiment, he contented himſelf with obtaining for a Favour, that ſhe would not diſcover him; which <hi>Yolanda</hi> had granted with ſome difficulty, upon condition, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, he ſhould never ſee her more, and that he would go and aſſure from her the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> That ſhe would be faithful to him until death. <hi>Judge now, after this,</hi> continued he, <hi>if you be not the moſt happy of all Men.</hi> The Prince well knowing that Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſpoke to him in good earneſt, was very well ſatisfied with hearing all theſe Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and was cured by this faithful Teſtimony of all the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſts
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:58385:28"/>which his Friends Diſguiſe had raiſed in him.</p>
                  <p>New Endeavours were again uſed to prevail with the Queen to abate of her Severity, and grant an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Pardon to Don <hi>Auguſtin;</hi> but her Majeſty would not hear of any thing more in his favour: He was conducted under Guard to <hi>Barcelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> where he was embarqued in the firſt Ship that departed for <hi>Sicily,</hi> accompanied with a ſevere Guide, who had expreſs Orders to ſee the Queens Pleaſure punctually execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. The ſecond Day of their em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barquing, they were ſurpriſed by a furious Tempeſt, which caſt 'em upon the Coaſts of <hi>Barbary,</hi> where they were upon the point of periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Main-maſt of the Ship bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and moſt of the Tackling ſhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd. They ſpent a whole Night between Death and Life. On the morrow, it was no ſooner day, than that they were diſcovered by a <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh</hi> Ship, who taking notice of the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:58385:28"/>ill Condition the Tempeſt had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced them to, attaqued 'em, and took 'em after a weak Reſiſtance. Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> being become a Slave, thought that his Diſguiſe would be to his advantage, well knowing, that amongſt the Nations the moſt Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous they have Regards for the Fair Sex. He was not miſtaken; for the Corſair who took 'em find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this pretended Maiden very much to his mind, he treated her with more Lenity than is uſual to thoſe of his Profeſſion. He was not long without making known to him his Paſſion; but the Reſiſtance of Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> having but augment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, he thought he could not free himſelf from his Importunities, but by declaring to him the truth of his Sex. Nevertheleſs, this Confeſſion did not produce upon the Spirit of the Corſair the Effect Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> expected it would have done.</p>
                  <p>Whilſt that Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the Injuſtice of this <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian,</hi>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:58385:29"/>the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta</hi> was not without Employ at <hi>Madrid.</hi> The Counteſs of <hi>Caſtelmara</hi> being gained by the good Offices the Marchioneſs of <hi>Villa-Franca</hi> had rendred her at Court, had eſpouſed her Intereſts, and out of acknowledgment gave her notice of the Paſſion which the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta</hi> had for <hi>Yolanda,</hi> and of the perfect Underſtanding of thoſe two Perſons; aſſuring her however, if ſhe could by her Credit ſend away the Prince, ſhe might hope in a ſhort time to gain the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of <hi>Yolanda.</hi> The Marchioneſs approving of this Advice, put all in practice, to oblige the Court to ſend back the Prince into <hi>Sicily.</hi> She found therein ſuch Difficulties as ſhe had not foreſeen, and perceived that the Chief Miniſter, who was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to keep ſome Meaſures with a Nobleman of that Quality, was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſed to gratifie him with one Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy or other before his departure. The Marchioneſs fearing the Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:58385:29"/>might be deferred, laboured for him with the ſame eagerneſs ſhe could have done for the Intereſts of her own Son: She obtained, in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of him, a Regiment of Foot in <hi>Sicily.</hi> The Prince very much ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pris'd at a Boon that was granted him, without his having ſolicited it, had a ſecret Vexation at this Mark of Eſteem which he thought he was honoured with by the Court; and thought this Employment did agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably flatter his Ambition, he could not reſolve to accept a Favour which ſeparated him from the Perſon in the World he loved with moſt Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: But Decency and his Courage not allowing him to refuſe an Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion which would afford him the Means of diſtinguiſhing himſelf from the young Perſons of his Age, he reſolved to depart, that ſo he might not render himſelf unworthy of the kind Diſpoſitions of the Court. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, not being able to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine himſelf to this departure with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:58385:30"/>taking leave of <hi>Yolanda,</hi> he in vain tried ſeveral Means to obtain leave to make her a Viſit: The Marchioneſs of <hi>Villa-Franca</hi> making it her Buſineſs to hinder this Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view, rendred the thing impoſſible; and the enamoured Prince deſpair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of bringing it about, addreſſed himſelf to the Counteſs of <hi>Caſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mara,</hi> and in ſhort deſired her to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver one Letter more from him to <hi>Yolanda.</hi> This perfidious Lady, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having made a great deal ado to excuſe her from medling in that matter, pretending at length to be moved and overcome by the exceſs of his Paſſion, promiſed him to take upon her to do it; and the Prince overjoyed with having gained her, in hopes ſhe would acquit her ſelf of it with the ſame Fidelity ſhe had done in the former, gave her this Letter.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:58385:30"/> 
                     <hi>I</hi> Go away in the higheſt deſpair. I am forced to accept of an Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which I cannot refuſe without diſhonouring my ſelf, or without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcovering the Charm which ſtays me at the Court. Tho' I ſaw you not there, I found a ſenſible pleaſure in being in the ſame Place, and of wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with ſome ſmall hopes the Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſpeaking to you a Moment. I will do all I can to revenge your Quarrel, and my own. I'll never par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> either the Death of your Father, or the Honour they do me in giving me an Employment which ſeparates me from you. I am not worthy to love you, and I refer all to my Heart. I abandon my ſelf to my Paſſion with ſo extreme a Reſignation, that I cannot fear you ſhould forget me. I ſhall think of you every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my Life, and ſhall never have a happy Minute but when I ſee you.</q>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:58385:31"/>
                  <p> As ſoon as the Prince was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, the Counteſs, in ſtead of carrying his Letter to <hi>Yolanda,</hi> as ſhe had engaged her ſelf to do, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed it to the Marchioneſs of <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la-Franca;</hi> who judging by the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate Terms in which it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that the Prince ſtood in no ill terms in <hi>Yolanda</hi>'s Breaſt, applied all her Cares to break off this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce: Nay, ſhe was upon the point of ſhewing this Letter to the Queen, to irritate her Majeſty againſt the Prince; but ſhe was diverted from it thro' the fear ſhe had of giving ſome diſadvantageous Impreſſion of <hi>Yolanda</hi>'s Conduct, whom ſhe alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy looked upon as her Daughter-in-Law. She was ſo ſatisfied with the Offices of the Counteſs of <hi>Caſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mara,</hi> that ſhe procured her ſeveral Occaſions of ſeeing <hi>Yolanda,</hi> and of contracting a particular Friendſhip with her; which was eaſie for her to do, under the colour of diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing her upon the Affairs of <hi>Sicily.</hi>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:58385:31"/>One day that they were alone, the Counteſs cunningly let the Diſcourſe fall upon the Princes departure: ſhe ſpoke of his Merit with all the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem and Conſideration that the beſt of his Friends could have done. <hi>Yolanda,</hi> deceived by this Artifice, and overjoyed to ſee the Counteſs in Sentiments ſo conformable to her own, loved her the more for it, and always made her a kind Reception from that time. The Counteſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted the Marchioneſs with this happy beginning, and with all the Diſcourſe ſhe had entertained <hi>Yolan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> with in favour of the Prince, for the gaining her Confidence, and for the being afterwards in a better ſtate to injure her Lover. The Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs approved of her Cunning. They had ſeveral Conferences to concert the Means for the well-managing of their Project. The experience they both had in ſuch like Affairs, made 'em both judge that Jealouſie was an infallible Expedient to alter the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:58385:32"/>good Intelligence of thoſe two Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and that if they could inſtil it into <hi>Yolanda,</hi> it would contribute much towards the promoting of their Deſign. To bring this about the more eaſily, the Marchioneſs caſt her Eyes upon a Maid of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour who had been brought up near her, and having perſwaded her that the Counteſs of <hi>Caſtelmara</hi> and ſhe had onely a mind to put a Sham up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Yolanda,</hi> to divert 'emſelves there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by afterwards, when they ſhould have diſcovered her real Sentiments for the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> and that it imported 'em, for the bringing this about, to perſuade her ſhe had a Rival; this young Lady, being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed to find an occaſion of making her ſelf merry, promiſed the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs to play the Part ſhe deſired. After this Engagement, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought themſelves of changing the Cover of the Letter which the Prince had left for <hi>Yolanda,</hi> to counterfeit the Superſcription the beſt they
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:58385:32"/>were able, and to addreſs it to Don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na <hi>Thereſa Gomes</hi> (which is the Name of the pretended Rival.) Theſe two Women having ſo well diſpoſed all things, the Counteſs, who had already acquired a great deal of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit in <hi>Yolanda</hi>'s good Opinion, ſtill pretending of her never having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of the Good will ſhe had for the Prince, told her one day, out of a kind of Confidence, That ſhe was very much miſtaken if the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta</hi> had not an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue with one of the Maids of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; nay, and that ſince his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſhe had obſerved a certain Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, mingled with a great deal of Diſquiet, in one of her Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, which confirmed her in her Opinion. This Artifice had the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for Effect; for <hi>Yolanda</hi> falling into this Snare, ſhew'd her ſelf very earneſt to know the Name of her Rival, and to be informed of the Circumſtances of this Intrigue. The Counteſs cunningly managing this
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:58385:33"/>Affair, told her, That perhaps ſhe made a raſh Judgment, and that ſhe would dive into the Truth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe acquainted her with any thing further. This Reſervedneſs augmenting the impatient Curioſity of <hi>Yolanda,</hi> ſhe deſired her never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs to tell her what ſhe knew thereof; but the Counteſs perſiſting not to do it, for fear, ſaid ſhe, of wounding her Conſcience, by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming a thing which ſhe was not very ſure of; <hi>Yolanda,</hi> without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo contented, conjured her to acquaint her at leaſt with the Name of the Perſon. Then the Counteſs, pretending that ſhe could no longer reſiſt her preſſing Importunities, own'd to her at length, that it was Donna <hi>Thereſa,</hi> beſeeching her that ſhe would reſt her ſelf ſo ſatisfied, in the aſſurance that ſhe gave her, carefully to apply her ſelf to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver if ſhe were not miſtaken. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſhe retired; and <hi>Yolanda</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alone, was racked with a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:58385:33"/>ſeveral Suſpicions. After ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Conflicts, wherein her Love had much ado to comfort her againſt her Jealouſie, ſhe reſolved to ſuſpend her Reſentment, and to wait until the Counteſs, in whom ſhe had an entire Confidence, had ſifted into this Affair. Two days after, the Counteſs having met with <hi>Yolanda,</hi> told her, That ſhe had wherewith to content her Curioſity, having learnt things which ſhe ſhould not dare to tell her, unleſs ſhe was aſſured of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſecret. <hi>Yolanda</hi> having paſſed her word ſhe would, the Counteſs added, That ſince ſhe had ſeen her laſt, ſhe had inſinuated her ſelf fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into the Confidence of Donna <hi>Thereſa,</hi> who had owned to her the perfect Intelligence which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween her and the Prince of <hi>Eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letta;</hi> nay, that ſhe had ſhewn her a Letter which ſhe had received from him. <hi>I muſt own to you,</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued the Counteſs, <hi>that I was a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſurpriſed at a Secret of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:58385:34"/>ſeeing nevertheleſs that ſhe did not bluſh, I thought I might diſpence my ſelf from bluſhing for her. This, my Fair One, is all I have learnt of the Affairs of the Prince of</hi> Eſcaletta. <hi>Yolanda</hi> had much ado to conceal her Jealouſie, and forbear exclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the Prince, whom ſhe thought unfaithful. By good luck, other Perſons came into the Place where they were talking, which gave <hi>Yolanda</hi> occaſion to withdraw. The Counteſs obſerving the great Effect which this forged Secret had produced upon the Mind of the too credulous <hi>Yolanda,</hi> went to rejoyce with the Marchioneſs for the happy Succeſs of their Artifice, adviſing her to finiſh what they had ſo happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begun, to ſee the new Donna <hi>Thereſa,</hi> and to put into her Hands the Princes Letter, that ſhe might oblige her to ſhew the Writing of it to <hi>Yolanda,</hi> yet without ſuffering her to read what it contained, not to give her any occaſion of ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:58385:34"/>their Cheat. The Marchioneſs knowing of what Conſequence it was to her, for the ſucceſs of her Deſigns, to follow the Counſels of the Counteſs, ſpoke thereof to Don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na <hi>Thereſa,</hi> who promis'd her to do all ſhe preſcrib'd to her, not diſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Marchioneſs, who was her great Friend, and who flatter'd her ſometimes with the Hopes that ſhe might be her Daughter-in-Law, would exact any thing from her which could do her any injury.</p>
                  <p>It would be a hard matter to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the dolorous Eſtate that <hi>Yolan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> was reduced to, when ſhe no longer doubted of the Infidelity of her Lover. Spite, Anger, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, did equally rend her Breaſt. Love, which in ſuch like Occaſions always ſpeaks in favour of the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, in vain endeavoured to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to her the Prince leſs culpable; not being able to reſolve to baniſh him from her Heart, tho' being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of his Crime, ſhe ſought for
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:58385:35"/>at leaſt ſome Pretext that might help to deceive her. After a thouſand different Thoughts, ſhe at length came to this Determination, by a laſt effort of her Paſſion, to inform her ſelf with her own Eyes, and to ſee often Donna <hi>Thereſa,</hi> flattering her ſelf, that ſhe would ſhew her that Criminal Letter, ſince ſhe had made no difficulty of ſhewing it to the Counteſs. As ſoon as ſhe had taken this Reſolution, her Thoughts were wholly bent upon putting it in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution. Donna <hi>Thereſa,</hi> on her ſide, being deſirous to pleaſe the Counteſs, by acquitting her ſelf handſomly of the Engagements ſhe was under, watched too for Opportunities of meeting alone with <hi>Yolanda.</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving both the ſame Deſign, it was no hard matter for them to meet. They diſcourſed for a pretty while upon indifferent things, each endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to cover her Deſign. Don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na <hi>Thereſa,</hi> whoſe Thoughts were more diſengaged, asked her if ſhe
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:58385:35"/>had not ſeen a very fine Song, which was much eſteemed by all the Court? <hi>Yolanda,</hi> whoſe Heart and Mind were extremely poſſeſſed, made her anſwer coldly, That ſhe was no Lover of Poetry: But a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection made her perceive that it became her not to ſeem ſo concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; ſhe asked to ſee it, and Donna <hi>Thereſa</hi> pretending to take it out of her Pocket, to give it her to read, preſented her the Letter of the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta. Yolanda</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Hand again at the firſt bluſh, was ſeiſed with ſuch Motions, that Donna <hi>Thereſa,</hi> pretending to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive her Errour, by the aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of her Companion, ſnatched the Letter haſtily out of her Hands, and gave her the Sonet in the ſtead of it, affecting a formal Confuſion, in having miſtaken the one for the other. There needed no more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely to ruine the unfortunate <hi>Yo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landa;</hi> ſhe could hardly hold from giving exceſſive marks of her De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:58385:36"/>after having ſeen ſo convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing a Proof of her Lovers Infidelity; and tho' before hand ſhe had thought ſhe had prepared her ſelf for all the Events of that dangerous Scrutiny, ſhe could not however forbear telling her Rival, That knowing the inconſtant Humors of the Cavaliers of her Nation, ſhe was willing to put her in mind not to rely much upon the Fidelity of the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> Donna <hi>Thereſa</hi> being willing to puſh on her Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, replied, That ſhe was not at all uneaſie upon the matter, and was well aſſured of the ſincerity of his Sentiments. <hi>Yolanda</hi> being no longer able to ſupport ſo painful a Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and perceiving that her Tears would betray her, if ſhe delayed withdrawing, deſired Donna <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſa</hi> to leave with her that Sonet to copy it, and under that pretence ſhe ſhut her ſelf up in her Chamber, where ſhe abandoned her ſelf to Grief. She ſaw no Condition more
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:58385:36"/>unhappy than hers, when ſhe repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to her ſelf the averſion ſhe had to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> the Reaſons ſhe thought obliged her to be reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on them, and the Promiſe the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta</hi> had made her, of eſpouſing her Reſentment, which had formerly held the firſt place in her Heart, were incomparably be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Deſpair which the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of her Lover created in her. It is impoſſible to expreſs the piteous Eſtate theſe Conſiderations reduced her to; deprived of her Parents and Relations, exil'd, as I may ſay, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt her Enemies, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſource, without hopes: all yielded to the horrour of not being belov'd, and of ſeeing her ſelf deceived by a Man whom ſhe thought ſo worthy of her Affections.</p>
                  <p>In the mean while the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, who had been informed by Donna <hi>Thereſa,</hi> took new meaſures with the Counteſs; and as ſhe knew, that when a Lady is fully
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:58385:37"/>perſwaded that ſhe has been failed, that time is the moſt proper to ſpeak in favour of another, they reſolved to make uſe of that occaſion to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Marriage of the Duke of <hi>Fernandina.</hi> The Counteſs charged her ſelf with all, and having viſited <hi>Yolanda,</hi> whom ſhe found very ſad, ſhe held her a long Diſcourſe upon the State of the Affairs of <hi>Sicily,</hi> and upon the particular Misfortunes of the Houſe of <hi>Cigala,</hi> and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the neceſſity ſhe was in to ſupport it, to marry a Man of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, who ſtood well at Court, and who might by his Credit re-eſtabliſh it in its former Splendour. <hi>Yolanda</hi> was ſo oppreſſed with grief, that ſhe hearkned to this Diſcourſe with as much indifference, as if ſhe had no ſhare therein. The Counteſs think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by her ſilence that ſhe reliſhed her Reaſons, continued, extolling the Birth, Perſonal Merit, and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Duke of <hi>Fernandina,</hi> (who perhaps would ſuddenly be nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:58385:37"/>Vice-Roy of <hi>Sicily</hi>) adding, That ſhe ſaw no Man that was a fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Match for her, nor who was more capable of raiſing up again the Grandeur of her Family. <hi>Yolanda</hi> being afraid ſhe would never have done, interrupted her with ſaying. That it was to no purpoſe to tell her of all thoſe great Advantages, ſince ſhe had an intention to ſpend her Life in a Convent. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs attributing this Anſwer to the firſt Motion of ſpite which ſhe knew <hi>Yolanda</hi> muſt needs have for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Infidelity of her Lover, and <hi>Yolanda</hi> having declared that ſhe was obliged to be at the Queens Apartment, an end was put to this Converſation, without the Counteſs knowing her ſelf what there was to hope or fear.</p>
                  <p>While that all this paſſed at <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta</hi> was at <hi>Meſſina,</hi> where he was continually thinking on the means of ſeeing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain his Miſtreſs. The Nobility of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:58385:38"/>the City had frequent Conferences at that time with the Senators, to endeavour together the preſerving the Authority of the Senate, which the Governour diminiſhed every day. After ſeveral Deliberations, they found no means more lawful to prevent the Conſequences of it, than that of having recourſe to their Sovereign, and reſolved to ſend ſome one or other into <hi>Spain,</hi> for the carrying their Complaints to the King, againſt the Uſurpations of the Governour, for to penetrate once for all, if all the Means which the Governours uſed to debaſe 'em, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from a particular Hatred which they had againſt 'em, or from an Order of the Court. The Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta</hi> ſeeing that Diſpoſition, employed all his Friends to obtain that Employment, in hopes that being Ambaſſadour, they could no longer deny to let him ſee his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs; but the remembrance of the ill Treatments the Houſe of <hi>Cigala</hi>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:58385:38"/>had received from the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and the hatred they nouriſh'd upon that account in their Hearts, made 'em prefer Don <hi>Philip Cigala, Yolanda</hi>'s Uncle, before the Prince of <hi>Eſcalet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> in an Employment wherein the main Buſineſs was to maintain their Liberty, and oppoſe the Jealouſie of the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> The Prince having notice hereof, comforted himſelf for the Refuſal he had met with, in hopes that Don <hi>Philip,</hi> who eſpouſed his Intereſts, and was his particular Friend, would ſuddenly bring back his Niece. He was the firſt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate this new Ambaſſador, and preſs him forthwith to depart. Don <hi>Philip</hi> embarqued ſhortly after, and promiſed the Prince to do his good Offices in his favour with <hi>Yolanda.</hi> But the Counteſs of <hi>Caſtelmara</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had notice of this <hi>Meſſineſe's</hi> departure, gave the Marchioneſs of <hi>Villa-Franca</hi> to underſtand, That it was of the greateſt conſequence to her, to prepoſſeſs the Miniſters as
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58385:39"/>to this Voyage, and to traverſe the Negotiation of Don <hi>Philip,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe had received notice, That this Ambaſſador came away with deſign to carry back his Niece, which would abſolutely ruine the Project of the Duke of <hi>Fernandina</hi>'s Match. The Counteſs found it no hard matter to perſuade the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, the Council of <hi>Spain</hi> having long before taken the reſolution to deſtroy the Senate of <hi>Meſſina,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the reſiſtance the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Governours met with in that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity.</p>
                  <p>Don <hi>Philip</hi> being arrived at <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid,</hi> they took the Pretext not to to receive him, by refuſing him the Quality of Ambaſſador. tho' they had never made any difficulty to give that Title to the Deputies of the City of <hi>Meſſina;</hi> and far from hearkning to the Remonſtrances and Submiſſions, it was taken into deliberation, whether the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor ſhould be taken into cuſtody.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:58385:39"/>Don <hi>Philip</hi> having had ſecret notice hereof, gave 'em not time to execute their Deſigns, and retired in all haſte, without ſo much as having ſeen his Niece, not daring to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture going to the Palace, for fear of being ſeiſed on. The <hi>Meſſineſes</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Don <hi>Philip</hi> return with ſo little ſatisfaction, were ſo provoked by the Contempt the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had of their Submiſſions, that they no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger doubted of the ill-will of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> whom they looked upon as Perſecutors; and ſince that time, the Troubles of <hi>Meſſina</hi> have ever been augmenting.</p>
                  <p>What ſhare ſoever that the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta</hi> took in the Publick Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, hearing of the ill ſucceſs of his Friends Voyage, the Intereſt of his Love contributed very much to the making him deteſt the unjuſt Proceedings of the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> He complained thereof to all the World, and ſpoke of it in ſuch Terms as ſufficiently gave to underſtand, that
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:58385:40"/>he intereſted himſelf in this Buſineſs after another manner than what concerned the Publick. The fear of ſeeing a <hi>Spaniard</hi> Poſſeſſor of his Miſtreſs, gave him continual Alarms; and onely thinking how to hinder this Misfortune, he had ſeveral Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences with the Relations of the Houſe of <hi>Cigala,</hi> who gave with delight their Conſent to his Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age with <hi>Yolanda.</hi> There was now nothing more to do, than to have her brought back from <hi>Spain;</hi> and this was what troubled the Prince moſt, upon the Difficulties he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saw in this Return. He would not have ſtuck returning to <hi>Madrid,</hi> and demanding her of the Queen, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded with the Conſent of her Relations, which he could eaſily have obtained in Writing; but the knowledge he had of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Policy, made him with reaſon fear, that his Love would be made in him a Crime of State, and that perhaps it might be laid hold on for an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:58385:40"/>of taking him into cuſtody, for having abandoned without Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Employment which the Court had confided in him the Year foregoing. All theſe Reaſonings augmented his Diſquiets, and his Paſſion was too ſtrong to permit him to be calm, being ſeparated from what he loved, with ſo little like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood of meeting in a good while.</p>
                  <p>Don <hi>Thomas Caraffo,</hi> who had married a Lady of the Houſe of <hi>Cigala,</hi> by whom he had ſeveral Children, and who by his Quality, his Age, and his Credit, was the Perſon who gave moſt weight to all the Deliberations of the Family, for the bringing about the Pretenſions of the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> was of opinion to interpoſe the Authority of the Prince of <hi>Ligne,</hi> at that time Viceroy of <hi>Sicily,</hi> and very much beloved by the <hi>Meſſineſes,</hi> for the knowledge they had of his Equity, and of his Humour, an Enemy to all Violences. The Sentiment of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:58385:41"/>Don <hi>Thomas Caraffo</hi> having been ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of, he himſelf had in charge to go to <hi>Palermo,</hi> to deſire the Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy to write to <hi>Spain,</hi> for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the return of <hi>Yolanda.</hi> The Prince <hi>de Ligne</hi> received him very obligingly, and wrote accordingly to the Queen in Terms very preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, beſeeching Her Majeſty to ſend back <hi>Yolanda</hi> to her Relations, who paſſionately deſired it, looking upon her as the Reſource and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of all their Family; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, That if her Majeſty thought fitting, <hi>Yolanda</hi> might repaſs into <hi>Italy</hi> with the new Dutcheſs of <hi>Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuna,</hi> who was going to her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band in his Government of <hi>Milan.</hi> The hopes the Prince had of obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome Advantage by the Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roys Interceſſion, gave ſome kind of Allay to his corroding Thoughts.</p>
                  <p>The Queen having received the Prince of <hi>Ligne</hi>'s Letter, was at firſt willing to grant him his Demand; nay, ſhe ſpoke thereof to <hi>Yolanda,</hi>
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:58385:41"/>declaring to her, that ſhe was loth to conſent to her departure, out of the affection ſhe had to her Perſon. But this Buſineſs coming to the Ears of the Marchioneſs of <hi>Villa-Franca,</hi> ſhe ſet ſo many Machins a going to hinder it, that the Affair was put into deliberation. She infuſed into the Miniſters, That <hi>Yolanda</hi> being one of the richeſt Matches, and of one of the Principal Families of <hi>Sicily,</hi> it did extremely import the King's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to have her married to a <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard,</hi> who might with ſuch conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Riches render great Services to the State, and diſſipate by his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and by his Cares, all the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals which began already to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at <hi>Meſſina</hi> againſt the Service of the King of <hi>Spain.</hi> The Reaſons of the Marchioneſs were ſo proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that ſhe eaſily perſuaded what ſhe deſired, and it was reſolved in the Council, That the Queen ſhould make anſwer to the Viceroy of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cily,</hi> and let him know, That ſhe
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:58385:42"/>would have agreed to <hi>Yolanda</hi>'s re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to her Relations, but that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſatisfied with her Services, ſhe thought her ſelf bound, out of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment, to detain her ſome time longer, not being able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to ſuffer her to depart from the Court, without giving her Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of her Eſteem; and that ſhe was in hopes to procure her quickly a Husband, who ſhould be worthy of her, and with whom her Relations ſhould have ever reaſon to be ſatisfied.</p>
                  <p>The Prince <hi>de Ligne</hi> having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived this Anſwer, ſent it to Don <hi>Thomas Caraffo,</hi> who imparted it to the other Relations; they quickly concluded, that it had been concerted in the Council, and that the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> thought leſs of giving a grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Eſtabliſhment to <hi>Yolanda,</hi> than of hindring her Riches from falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſuſpected Family. They meant to conceal this ill. News from the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta;</hi> but his Love,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:58385:42"/>which made him fear the worſt, had given him ſecret pre-ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this Anſwer. He had like to have died of grief, when <hi>Yo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landa</hi>'s Relations told him the truth of the matter: They reſolved, for his comfort, that Don <hi>Philip Cigala</hi> ſhould write a Letter to his Niece, in the Name of all the Family, by which he ſhould let her know the extreme deſire that all her Family had to ſee her married to the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> and that they hoped, from the goodneſs of her Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that ſhe would defere to the Choice of her Relations; nay, that ſhe would repreſent to the Queen this Engagement, if it hapned that her Majeſty would propoſe to her any other Match. Tho' all theſe Paces were feeble enough, the Prince, who could do nothing better in the preſent ſtate, and who ſtill recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned upon the Inclination which his Miſtreſs had for him, flattered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that this Letter would produce
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:58385:43"/>a good Effect, and that at leaſt it might help <hi>Yolanda</hi> to defend her ſelf, upon this pretext, from enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging her ſelf to any body without the Conſent of her Relations, for fear of incurring the anger of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> never fail of threatning their diſobedient Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with, and which they always give for a Pretext to their Deſigns.</p>
                  <p>There hapned at that time great Broils between the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and the <hi>Meſſineſes,</hi> the Nobility having ſtrongly oppoſed ſome Novelty, which the Governour of the City would have introduced, without the participation of the Senate: But this Diſorder was quickly appeaſed by the Care and Vigilance of the Prince <hi>de Ligne,</hi> who ſtill diverted the Storm, and perhaps that if he had been believed, the affairs of <hi>Meſſina</hi> would not have run ſo counter to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> having ſeveral times given the Court notice of the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of the <hi>Sicilians,</hi> who are the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:58385:43"/>People in the World the moſt jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of the Preſervation of their Privileges: But no Ear was given to his Advices, and the Council of <hi>Spain,</hi> that had for a long while pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected the Ruine of the Senate of <hi>Meſſina,</hi> as I have already ſaid, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king new Umbrages from the Union of the Senators with the Nobility, thought of executing this Deſign; and not being willing to employ main Force, leſt they ſhould alarm the other Cities of the Kingdom, they thought they might more eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bring it about by Artifice: For that purpoſe they ſtood in need of a Man of Wit, who knew well how to diſſemble his real Sentiments: And as in all ſorts of Nations there are not wanting Perſons of that Character, thoſe who were of the Secret pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed ſeveral Perſons, whom they judged very proper for the bringing about this Deſign. Don <hi>Lewis de Loya,</hi> whoſe Genius was known, and who in ſuch like Occaſions had,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:58385:44"/>given Marks of his Ability, was preferred before all the others, and was ſent to <hi>Meſſina</hi> in Quality of <hi>Stratico,</hi> (ſo call they the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.) This Charge, which after that of Viceroy is the moſt conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Kingdom of <hi>Sicily,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been confided in Don <hi>Lewis de Loya,</hi> with ſecret Memoires of the Intentions of the Court, he depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſecure of the Protection of the Miniſters, and full of the great Hopes that were given him, in caſe he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed the deſtroying the Senate of <hi>Meſſina</hi> by his Cunning. He had given him all the Powers neceſſary for acting, neither were they ſparing of great Sums of Money for the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitating all things to him. The Viceroy of <hi>Sicily</hi> had Order not to meddle at all with the particular Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of <hi>Meſſina,</hi> and to ſuffer Don <hi>Lewis</hi> to act as he ſhould think con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient. This new Governour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing arrived at <hi>Meſſina,</hi> applied him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf forthwith to grow well acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:58385:44"/>with the Humour and Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe with whom he had to do, truſting in that caſe onely to his own knowledg. Having obſerved, that the People of that Country ſuffer themſelves ſometimes to their diſadvantage, to be deceived by the Appearances of Piety, he fancied he might eaſily inſinuate himſelf into their good Opinion, by feigning a great Probity, ſeconded by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary Devotion. There is no ſort of Hypocriſie but which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought himſelf of, for the bringing this about: He often viſited the Churches, frequented the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; in ſhort, exerciſed ſuch a Piety as altogether reſembles that which is practiſed by People who are really Devout. And to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all pretext of Detraction, and hold from thoſe who knew him to the bottom, of blaming ſo holy a Conduct, he maintained his Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie with ſeveral conſiderable Alms, which he knew how to diſtribute
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:58385:45"/>with more Cunning than Piety, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying for that uſe the Money that was given him at his Departure. His Artifices had immediately the Effect he had promiſed to himſelf; for the People, who never dive into any thing, and judge of all things by the Appearances, looked upon Don <hi>Lewis</hi> as the Defender of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. He knew ſo well how to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have himſelf in his Diſſimulation, with ſo much artifice, that in a ſhort while the Publick was as fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded of the ſincerity of his Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as it was already of his Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
                  <p>As ſoon as Don <hi>Lewis</hi> found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the good Opinion of the Common People to his Hearts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, he made uſe of the Credit which his Artifices had acquired him, for to inſpire into 'em an Averſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Senate, and againſt the Nobility. The Senators being well informed of the Deſigns of Don <hi>Lewis,</hi> neglected nothing for the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:58385:45"/>deſtroying his ill Intentions. They let thoſe ſee, who were not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed, that Don <hi>Lewis</hi> made it his whole Buſineſs to diſunite the Nobility and the People, onely that he might with the more eaſe cruſh 'em both afterwards.</p>
                  <p>While that the Affairs of <hi>Meſſina</hi> were in this ill diſpoſition, <hi>Yolanda</hi> was in no more tranquillity in the midſt of the Court, than her Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons amidſt Tumults and Seditions. She had received a Letter from Don <hi>Philip Cigala</hi> her Uncle, which had given her ſome Comfort, as much as her Love alarm'd was capable of Conſolation, in the unhappy Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances which the Intrigues of the Marchioneſs of <hi>Villa-Franca,</hi> and of the Counteſs of <hi>Caſtelmara,</hi> had reduced her to. Repaſſing in her Mind all the Circumſtances of that Letter, ſhe judged that her Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were deſirous of a Match be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween her and the Prince of <hi>Eſcalet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> out of Reaſons of Intereſt or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:58385:46"/>perhaps unknown to the Prince, or at leaſt perhaps without that Love had any ſhare therein. Theſe Reflexions augmented her anxiety, and the remembrance of her Lover's Infidelity put her in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair. The Counteſs was become ſuſpected to her, thro' the Intereſt ſhe had ſeen ſhe took in her Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age with the Duke of <hi>Fernandina.</hi> She was ſurrounded with People whom ſhe hated, and ſhe had not a Perſon of truſt, to whom ſhe could diſcover the real Sentiments of her Heart, which much contributed to the rendring her Misfortunes the more ſenſible; nothing in the World being ſo proper to allay our Evils, and principally Amorous Pains, as imparting 'em to a Confident. The Tears ſhe ſhed, and the Affliction which almoſt ever appeared in her Face, were not capable of bringing any great change to her Beauty, which was ſo perfect, that all the Court ſpoke of it with admiration.
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:58385:46"/>Thoſe who knew her not, were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely deſirous to ſee her, and ſhe was commonly called <hi>The Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Sicilian.</hi> Several young Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the Court ſighed for her, but not any of 'em had ever declared to her his Paſſion, by reaſon of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty there was of coming at her, and by the little opportunity ſhe afforded for ſo doing. In ſhort, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did a Beautiful Perſon ſpend more unpleaſantly the firſt Years of her Youth; and thoſe happy Times which two Lovers enjoy, who are not diſturbed in their Paſſion, had onely laſted for her as long as was neceſſary to make her the more lively ſenſible of the unhappy Eſtate ſhe was in.</p>
                  <trailer>The End of the Firſt Part.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58385:47"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58385:47"/>
                  <p>YOLANDA OF SICILY A NOVEL.</p>
                  <p>THE SECOND PART.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Bentley</hi> and <hi>S. Magnes,</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel-ſtreet</hi> near <hi>Covent-garden.</hi> MDCLXXXV.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="novel">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58385:48"/>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:58385:48"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>YOLANDA</hi> OF SICILY.</head>
                  <div n="2" type="part">
                     <head>PART II.</head>
                     <p>THe Marchioneſs of <hi>Villa-Franca,</hi> whom <hi>Yolanda</hi>'s Contempt neither made to deſpond, nor ceaſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting her Deſign, which ſhe was ſtill in hopes of effecting, either by Cunning or Compulſion, made freſh Inſtances to the Miniſters, to inſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inuate into their Minds the Marriage of the Duke of <hi>Fernandina</hi> with <hi>Yo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landa,</hi> as an Affair of State. The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:58385:49"/>Circumſtances of the Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of <hi>Meſſina,</hi> which augmented every day, contributed very much to the engaging on her Side the Count <hi>de Pennaranda,</hi> Preſident of the Council of <hi>Italy.</hi> The Count being perſuaded, that nothing could be done better for the Service of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and for the common Intereſt of the Nation, than to make the <hi>Spaniards</hi> enter into the Alliance of the Principal Families of <hi>Sicily,</hi> took the liberty to preſs the Buſineſs hard to the Queen; and ſeeing her Majeſty had a repugnance to give her Conſent, without conſulting the mind of <hi>Yolanda, Penneranda</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to her, That Perſons of a Great Rank do never marry by their Choice, ſince that the very Princeſſes of Sovereign Families are often Sacrifices to the Intereſts of the State, and become the Wives of thoſe whom they had looked upon as Enemies; ſo that <hi>Yolanda</hi>'s Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ought not to be any Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:58385:49"/>in this Buſineſs: That ſhe was perhaps of the humour of moſt young Women, who propoſe to 'emſelves nothing more in their eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment, than the ſatisfying their preſent Paſſion, and who never fail of being unhappy, when that their Fondneſs and Tranſports being cool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and diminiſhed, they come to conſider the ſtate they are in, and the ſtate they might have been in, if they had defered to the Sentiments of thoſe who were not prepoſſeſſed, as they were. The Count percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that the Queen was ſatisfied with his Reaſons, added, That the Duke of <hi>Fernandina</hi> had ſo many good Qualities, that he did not doubt but that <hi>Yolanda</hi> would love him, as ſoon as that ſhe knew him. There needed no more to perſuade the Queen fully. The Marriage was reſolved on, and the Queen took upon her ſelf to acquaint <hi>Yolanda</hi> with this News, who had long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected ſome ſuch like buſineſs. Her
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:58385:50"/>Majeſty ſpoke to her thereof, and let her know, that her Affection, and the deſire of ſeeing her well ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, had made her deſirous to ſee her united to the Duke of <hi>Fernandina,</hi> aſſuring her, That in favour of this Match, ſhe would give 'em both Teſtimonies of her Kindneſs, and of the ſatisfaction ſhe took therein. <hi>Yo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landa,</hi> diſſembling out of reſpect the Spite which theſe Tidings created in her, thanked the Queen for her Goodneſs, and anſwered, That ſhe had nothing to reply to what her Majeſty commanded her; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, that ſhe moſt humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeched her to give her time to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Conſent of her Relations, that ſo ſhe might not incur the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Heaven by ſo manifect a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect. The Queen gave her leave to write to 'em thereof, and order'd her nevertheleſs to prepare her ſelf to depart within three Months, to go to the Duke of <hi>Fernandina</hi> at <hi>Naples.</hi> The Counteſs of <hi>Caſtelmara,</hi>
                        <pb n="95" facs="tcp:58385:50"/>pretending a great ſurpriſe at ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den a Reſolution, went to <hi>Yolanda,</hi> to ſift her Mind upon the matter: But ſhe made her anſwer with ſo much reſervedneſs, that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs found it very difficult to pry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her real Sentiments. Then ſhe uſed extraordinary Efforts, to make her reſolve to obey with a good Grace: But <hi>Yolanda,</hi> who had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared her ſelf for theſe Violences, had at firſt took her Reſolution, and was determined to die, when that ſhe ſhould ſee there was no more reſource, and to conceal in the mean while her Reſolution, hoping that Time, her Relations, or perhaps the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> might work ſome Change. Thus ſhe did not vent her Reſentment into impertinent Diſcourſes, but made the Counteſs anſwer, and all thoſe who made her Complements upon this Marriage, that ſhe expected with ſubmiſſion the Anſwer of the Will of her Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. The Marchioneſs of <hi>Villa-Franca</hi>
                        <pb n="96" facs="tcp:58385:51"/>would needs make and give a noble Preſent to this fair future Bride. <hi>Yolanda,</hi> without refuſing it, deſired her to give her leave not to receive it, until the Conſent of her Family was arrived. The Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs could not take offence at ſo prudent an Anſwer, and <hi>Yolanda,</hi> by ſo handſom a Conduct, deceived the Vigilance of thoſe who watch'd her, and found means to give her Relations an Account of the ſtate ſhe was in, and of the Deſign ſhe had to prefer Death, before the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage that was propoſed to her.</p>
                     <p>As ſoon as her Relations knew the Reſolution that was taken in <hi>Spain,</hi> they had divers Conferences for the contriving the Means of hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring this Marriage, and of deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Yolanda.</hi> All the Nobility joyn'd with'em, and complained publickly of this Injuſtice. The Governour, pretending he would appeaſe 'em, went to the Palace where the Senate does aſſemble, and having cauſed
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:58385:51"/>the Senators to come thither, he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Gates to be ſhut up, with deſign to have 'em all put to death. Don <hi>Antonio Caraffo</hi> having notice of the Peril which menaced his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, went to the Palace, with a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution either to free him, or to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. He was followed with ſo nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous a Populace, that the Captain of the Governour's Guards was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid that all was upon the point of being loſt, and that they were go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſet fire to the Palace, if the Senators were not quickly ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. He gave notice thereof to the Governour, who cauſed the Gates to be opened, and ſent 'em all back.</p>
                     <p>The Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to know what would be the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue of all theſe Diſorders, knowing that the term of his Miſtreſſes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture did approach, and not being able to imagine a greater Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, than to ſee her in the Arms of his Rival, was inceſſantly contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the means of ſecuring her from
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:58385:52"/>this Violence. His Friends and her Relations were ſo taken up to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves againſt the Inſults of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and to detain the Populace, provoked by the Chears of the Governour, that they had not time to think of giving ſuccour to <hi>Yolanda,</hi> nor aſſiſt with their Counſels the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta.</hi> Thus this unhappy Lover, having no more proſpect of any reſource, abandoned himſelf to all the Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients which his Deſpair inſpired him with; and having made Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of Money and Jewels, he went away for <hi>Algiers,</hi> and put himſelf into the Hands of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Corſair <hi>Trik,</hi> whom he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to engage in his Intereſts, by the Preſents which he heaped upon him, and by the Diſcourſes, filled with Flattery, wherewith he accompanied his Liberalities, own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him ſincerely, that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of his Valour had obliged him to court his Protection, for the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:58385:52"/>delivering his Miſtreſs from the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> This Corſair immediately promiſed to ſerve him, with aſſurances, that he ſhould quickly know, that he was not deceived in the good Opinion which he had conceived of him.</p>
                     <p>Whereupon he armed two good Ships, and put to Sea, with a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of waiting for <hi>Yolanda,</hi> and of taking her when ſhe ſhould paſs into <hi>Italy.</hi> That Lovely Perſon was in the mean while under inconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable Diſquiets: The hideous Idea ſhe had formed to her ſelf of the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta</hi>'s Infidelity, had determined her to put her ſelf to death, when ſhe could no longer defer being the Wife of the Duke of <hi>Fernandina.</hi> Being upon the point of departing from <hi>Madrid,</hi> ſhe went to take leave of her Companions. Donna <hi>Thereſa de Gomez,</hi> who had long been in love with the Duke of <hi>Fernandina,</hi> had always flattered her ſelf with marrying him; and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:58385:53"/>ſeeing <hi>Yolanda</hi> was ready to depart, vex'd that a Stranger was going to fruſtrate her of her Hopes, by rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing her of the Man ſhe loved; and imagining that the Marchioneſs of <hi>Villa-Franca</hi> had joyned with <hi>Yolan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> to deceive her, when that they had engaged her to feign her being beloved by the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> the remembrance of this Injury, and the regret of loſing her Lover, touched her ſo to the quick, that ſhe could not forbear declaiming and tearing the Letter of the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> reproaching <hi>Yolanda</hi> with her Perfidiouſneſs, and complaining of her having been betray'd. <hi>Yolan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> ſurpriſed at this action, perceived by this Sally, and by the other Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſes with which Donna <hi>Thereſa</hi> held her, that they had been both deceived. She endeavoured to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe her, by a ſincere confeſſion of the Truth. But Donna <hi>Thereſa,</hi> who had her Mind prepoſſeſs'd, and who regulated the Sentiments of <hi>Yolanda</hi>
                        <pb n="101" facs="tcp:58385:53"/>for the Duke of <hi>Fernandina,</hi> by her own, not being able to underſtand how that any other could hate a Man whom ſhe found ſo amiable, refuſed to hear her, and without entring into any further clearing of the Point, ſhe retired in diſorder, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not the power to ſupport the preſence of a Rival whom ſhe thought happy.</p>
                     <p>After this Sally of Donna <hi>Thereſa, Yolanda</hi> did no longer doubt but that her Lover had ever been faithful to her; and this thought gave her the more horrour for the Marriage ſhe was threatned with. In the mean while, ſhe was nevertheleſs forced to reſolve on her departure. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs of <hi>Caſtelmara</hi> was encharged with her Conduct. They embarqued at <hi>Barcelona,</hi> in a Gally of <hi>Spain,</hi> which had order to carry 'em into <hi>Sicily.</hi> The Diſquiets of <hi>Yolanda</hi> augmented by the ſame degrees that ſhe approached her Country; and and tho' ſhe was in great hopes of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:58385:54"/>the Love of the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> and of the Kindneſs of her Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Authority of the Duke of <hi>Fernandina</hi> made her fear the worſt. She was in theſe agitations when that the Ships of <hi>Trik</hi> gave the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gally. The Efforts the Captain made to gain the Shore, were all to no purpoſe; but the Corſair had taken ſuch exact meaſures; that it was impoſſible for the <hi>Spaniard</hi> to avoid the Combate. The Match at firſt ſeemed very une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual, and there ſeemed to be teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in reſiſting two Ships ſo well armed: Nevertheleſs, the Captain, without being daunted by the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces of <hi>Trik,</hi> who had declared he would ſink him if he delayed yielding up the Gally, defended him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with great Valour, and gave to underſtand by his vigorous Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, that he would not ſuffer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be ſo eaſily taken as the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſair had imagined. The enamour'd Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta</hi> fearing that the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:58385:54"/>obſtinacy of this Captain would prove the deſtruction of his Miſtreſs, ſaw not one Broad ſide given which gave not cruel Alarms to his Love: He repreſented to himſelf every moment the Deſpair he ſhould be reduced to, if by misfortune he was going to be the Cauſe of <hi>Yolanda</hi>'s Death; and not being willing to expoſe any longer a Perſon whom he loved more than his own Life, he reſolved at length to periſh himſelf, or to ſecure her without hazarding the loſing her. This obliged him to deſire <hi>Trik</hi> to give him a Pinnace, with ſome Soldiers, to board the Gally with Sabre in hand. The Corſair, who was irritated by the raſh Reſiſtance of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> made ſome difficulty, pretending he would not expoſe him to ſo evident a danger, tho' in his Soul he was not ſorry for it, in hopes of gaining his Jewels, and perhaps that he might diſpoſe of <hi>Yolanda</hi> according to his own will and pleaſure, of whom he
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:58385:55"/>had framed to himſelf an agreeable Idea, by the Diſcourſes of her Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. The Prince having inſiſted in his demand of a Pinnace, the Corſair ſeemed to be overcome with repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and to yield to his Importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and gave it him, with thirty reſolute Soldiers, who boarded the Gally in ſpite of all the firing of the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> The Prince having fix'd upon the Captain, whom he eaſily diſtinguiſhed by his Valour, was ſo happy as to diſable him immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and imagining the <hi>Turks</hi> would without pain ſubdue the others, the impatience he was in to ſee his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, mingled with the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhe might be dead, made him abandon the care of purſuing his Victory, to learn news of her. What averſion ſoever <hi>Yolanda</hi> had for the Duke of <hi>Fernandina,</hi> the Image of Death, and the fear of being in a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time the Prey of a barbarous Corſair, had made her forget her Hatred, eſpecially after the Compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:58385:55"/>ſhe had for the Death of the Counteſs of <hi>Caſtelmara,</hi> who had been killed with a Cannon-ſhot. She implored the Succours of Heaven with a great Reſignation, when that the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> who was deſcended into the bottom of the Hole to ſee her, preſented himſelf before her eyes. It is eaſie to judge of <hi>Yolanda</hi>'s ſurpriſe, who expected nothing more than Death, ſeeing in that moment appear the onely Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the World who made her love Life. The Prince finding her in a very deplorable eſtate, <hi>Fear nothing, Madam,</hi> ſaid he to her, <hi>I am here to deliver you.</hi> The ſurpriſe ſhe was in at the ſight of her Lover, had like to have been more fatal to her than her Fear had been: She fell into a Swoon in the Arms of her Women, and the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta</hi> being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſured at the ſight of a Perſon who was ſo dear to him, thought of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than of rendring him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Maſter of the Gally, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:58385:56"/>again above deck in all haſte, without ſo much as perceiving <hi>Yo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landa</hi>'s being fallen into a Swoon. He found that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves with an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Opiniativeneſs; and animated with that noble Ardour which his Love inſpired him with, he ruſhed in amongſt 'em, and was ſo well ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by the <hi>Turks,</hi> that in a ſhort time he found no more Reſiſtance. But he could not gain ſo conſiderable Advantage, without being wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſeveral Places, tho' ſomewhat ſlightly. <hi>Trik,</hi> who was juſt come on board the Gally, having percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that the Prince loſt Blood, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to be carried away, in ſpite of his Reſiſtance, and gave order he ſhould be carried into a Ship, where an able Chirurgeon ſearched his Wounds.</p>
                     <p>The Corſair, in the mean while, ſearched all the Corners and Cranies of the Gally, where he thought any Money might be hid, as often hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:58385:56"/>in ſuch like Occaſions. <hi>Yolanda</hi> being recovered from her Swoon, and thinking to find the Prince, was terribly frighted to ſee the Corſair approach, whoſe Meen alone inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Terrour. <hi>Trik,</hi> ſtruck with the Luſtre of ſo ſurpriſing a Beauty, pauſed a moment to conſider her; and tho' ſhe ſeemed to him very amiable, his Avarice prevailed over all the Motions of his Heart, and the deſire of finding Money, which the <hi>Turks</hi> are more greedy of than all other Nations, obliged him to ask her if ſhe knew not where the Captain of the Gally had concealed his Treaſure. <hi>Yolanda,</hi> in ſtead of making him any anſwer, abandoned her ſelf to Tears, no longer doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but that ſhe was a Slave, and imagining that the exceſs of her Love had deceived her, when ſhe fancied, ſhe had ſeen the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Corſair, for his part, had his thoughts wholly bent on reaping
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:58385:57"/>the Spoils of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Captain, by cauſing what was moſt precious in the Gally to be tranſported into his Ships, the Gally being too much diſabled to avoid Shipwrack. He ordered that <hi>Yolanda</hi> ſhould be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into his own Ship, as well as ſeveral Travellers who had taken that occaſion of going into <hi>Italy. Yolanda</hi> was hardly got into the Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, than that the Gally-ſlaves were heard to cry out after a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table manner. Then they all perceived that the Gally was upon ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The Cries redoubled, and there aroſe a confuſion of piteous Voices of Perſons who were going to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, whereof ſeveral caſt 'emſelves into the Sea. Nay, <hi>Trik</hi> himſelf ran a great riſque, and ſaved himſelf by ſwimming, with ſome difficulty. They had juſt done ſearching the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta</hi>'s Wounds, which were found very ſlight, when that this doleful Noiſe ſtruck his Ears. His Love making him fear the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:58385:57"/>worſt, he crawled towards that ſide where the Gally was, which he ſaw diſappear in a moment; and not doubting but that his Miſtreſs was ſwallowed up by the Waves, becauſe he knew not of her having been conveyed into the other Ship, he onely gave ear to his Deſpair, and precipitated himſelf into the Sea, much leſs out of hopes of ſuccour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her, than not to ſurvive her. His Men having caſt 'emſelves in after him, ſaved him againſt his will, juſt in the nick of time he began no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be able to reſiſt the violence of the Billows, and carried him again on board, where he recovered his Spirits, by the care they took to make him vomit up the Water he had ſwallowed. But his Grief was not the leſs ſtrong, and turning to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Corſair, from whom he thought he had received the Help he had newly given him, <hi>What have I done, too generous</hi> Trik, ſaid he to him, <hi>for to oblige you to deprive me
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:58385:58"/>of the onely Comfort I have left, of accompanying in Death that Perſon who alone rendred Life ſupportable to me? Trik</hi> perceiving by this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe that the Prince was prepoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd of <hi>Yolanda</hi>'s being drowned, was not over-ſorry at his Errour, the Charms of that Beautiful Perſon having already inſpired him with Sentiments of Love. He confirmed to him the Death of his Miſtreſs, giving him to underſtand, that he had in vain uſed his Endeavours to ſave her, but that the Gally ſunk ſo ſuddenly, that he himſelf had like to have been buried in the Billows. The Prince finding his Grief re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed by the Diſcourſe of the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſair, would have ſtole away the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time to have flounced into the Sea; but he was prevented by his Men, who watched him with all the care imaginable, leſt he ſhould make himſelf away. <hi>Trik</hi> in the mean while went into the other Ship, under colour of giving there
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:58385:58"/>the Orders neceſſary, covering per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps with that pretext the preſſing deſire he had of ſeeing <hi>Yolanda,</hi> and of preventing either ſhe or the Prince having any Tidings of one another. He found her more charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing than ſhe had ſeemed to him the firſt time, and became paſſionately enamour'd. But as he had got a ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of making all his Sentiments ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to thoſe of his Avarice, and judging by the exceſs of his Paſſion, of <hi>Yolanda</hi>'s Beauty, he reſolved to carry her to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> where thoſe Women are ſold at a dear rate, as are handſom enough to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Seraglio</hi> of the <hi>Grand Seignior.</hi> The more he ſaw her, the more he found her to abound in Charms. <hi>Yolanda</hi> in the mean while recolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted all that had hapned to her in the Gally, and not being able to undeceive her ſelf, but that ſhe had ſeen the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> ſhe could not underſtand how he had diſappeared and vaniſhed ſo ſoon.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:58385:59"/>
                        <hi>Trik</hi> accoſting her, ſound her in a very deplorable condition, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to ſpeak to her, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to comfort her, and told her, That her Circumſtances were not ſo unhappy as ſhe imagined, ſince ſhe was fallen into the hands of a Man who had a great reſpect for Ladies, and that he ſhould be very ſorry to do any thing to diſpleaſe her. <hi>Yolan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> being deſirous to inform her ſelf whether ſhe had ſeen the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> or a Phantaſm, thanked <hi>Trik</hi> for his Civility, and told him, That the loſs of her Liberty was not what afflicted her moſt, having been long accuſtomed to Servitude; but that ſhe fancied ſhe had ſeen, before ſhe was brought on board that Ship, a Cavalier of her own Nation, in whom ſhe took a great deal of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and whom ſhe was afraid did periſh in the Gally. <hi>If it be the Prince of</hi> Eſcaletta <hi>you mean,</hi> ſaid the Corſair to her, <hi>I partake with you in the affliction for his death: He was
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:58385:59"/>my Friend, and I could not ſave him from the Shipwrack, what Endeavours ſoever. I uſed, and what Care and Pains ſoever I took to free him out of that Peril. He is then dead, and I was not miſtaken,</hi> cried the ſad <hi>Yo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landa:</hi> After which, Tears and Sobs ſtifled her Voice. This News did ſo ſenſibly afflict her, that ſhe would have drawn Compaſſion from a Heart leſs hardned than that of a Corſair. This wicked Wretch, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having given his Orders to the Officers, returned to the Ship where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Prince was on board, in a condition much like to that of <hi>Yo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landa,</hi> and as cruelly tormented for the loſs of his Miſtreſs, as ſhe had been afflicted at the Tidings of her Lover's being caſt away. <hi>Trik</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing already impatient to ſee him gone, repreſented to him, That it was unbecoming ſo great a Courage, to abandon himſelf to Grief; That he ought to reſolve upon ſomething without any farther delay; and that
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:58385:60"/>he would ſhew his Love much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by revenging his Miſtreſs, and by entertaining an irreconcileable Hatred againſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> than by ſuffering himſelf to be led away by an uſeleſs Deſpair. The Prince had a kind of ſcorn at the <hi>Turk</hi>'s Remonſtrances, and his Wounds not being ſo conſiderable as to hinder him from acting, he came of a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to a Determination, and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to return to <hi>Meſſina,</hi> with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of making there a cruel War upon the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> whom he look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon as the Authors of <hi>Yolanda</hi>'s Death. He deſired <hi>Trik</hi> to carry him into ſome Port where he might embarque for <hi>Meſſina;</hi> but being told how difficult it was to get thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by reaſon of the oppoſition of ſome <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ships which guarded the Coaſts, to hinder any Victuals or Proviſions being carried into <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſina,</hi> which they pretended to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce by Hunger, the Prince was obliged to embarque in a Ship which
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:58385:60"/>he met with by chance, bound for <hi>Venice,</hi> where he arrived two days after. At <hi>Venice</hi> he was informed, how that the Diſorders of <hi>Meſſina</hi> augmented every day, and that the Senate and Nobility, being reduced to extremity, had ſent Deputies to <hi>Rome,</hi> for the beſeeching the Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador of <hi>Spain</hi> to implore in favour of 'em the Clemency of the Queen Regent. The Prince extremely ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed at this News, went Poſt-haſte to <hi>Rome</hi> to hinder this Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, which deprived him of the Means and Occaſions of being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged on the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> He diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered at his arrival at <hi>Rome,</hi> that Don <hi>Antonio Caraffo</hi> was there, with two Senators, and that the Rumour which was ſpread abroad, of their being upon the point of an Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation with the Ambaſſador of <hi>Spain,</hi> was an Invention of <hi>Caraffo,</hi> who had found out that Expedient to make his Voyage with the more ſecurity, and to amuſe thoſe who
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:58385:61"/>were ſtill in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Party; tho' their Deſign was to take Meaſures with the Cardinal and Duke <hi>d' E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrees,</hi> to ſound if the Moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King was willing to take the City of <hi>Meſſina</hi> into his Protection. The Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> overjoyed at hearing a Reſolution ſo confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to his Sentiments, went to the Houſe of the Ambaſſador of <hi>France,</hi> and having made himſelf known, he was admitted to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Conferences which the Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Meſſina</hi> had with the Cardinal <hi>d' Eſtrees;</hi> but to no purpoſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that the <hi>Meſſineſes,</hi> who thought leſs to give 'emſelves to the <hi>French,</hi> than to ſatisfie their great and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Hatred againſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> were ſtill uncertain, the Diviſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo great among 'em, that ſome revoked what the others had conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Nevertheleſs, deſpairing of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reconciled with the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> Don <hi>Antonin Caraffo</hi> had order from the Senate to go into <hi>France,</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:58385:61"/>his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty to ſuccour the People of <hi>Meſſina.</hi> He found many Difficulties in making his Voyage, becauſe that the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards,</hi> who are better ſerved by their Spies than by their Captains, having notice thereof, ſent Scouts abroad, and way laid him, for the having him ſeiſed. But he traveſtied him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo well, that he deceived their Vigilance, and got into <hi>France,</hi> where he laid open the Occaſion of his Journey, and the Extremities the People of <hi>Meſſina</hi> were reduced to, who were brought to eat Inſects, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having conſumed their Horſes and their Dogs, and could not avoid periſhing either by Famine or by Rage, in the Reſolution they had taken, of preferring Death before the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Tyranny.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Lewis the Great,</hi> who has no leſs Compaſſion for the Miſerable, than he has Rigour for thoſe who dare oppoſe him, was ſo moved at the Oppreſſion of theſe poor People,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:58385:62"/>that he gave 'em great Succours in a time when the numerous Armies of the Allies in <hi>Flanders,</hi> that of the <hi>Germans</hi> upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> the Forces of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> and the great Fleet of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Coaſt of <hi>Britany,</hi> would have made a leſs courageous King think of the Defence of his Territories, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſending his Troops and his Ships to the further Ends of <hi>Europe,</hi> for the relieving an oppreſſed City, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally not being able to foreſee at that time, that the Conjuncture of Affairs would oblige him to withdraw 'em.</p>
                     <p>In the mean while, News came to <hi>Meſſina</hi> of the pretended Shipwrack of <hi>Yolanda.</hi> All the Nobility were equally concerned at it, ſome out of Intereſt of Blood, and others out of the Compaſſion they had of the Deſtiny of a Perſon of her Birth; and if they could have added any thing to the implacable Hatred they had already againſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> her Death would have very much
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:58385:62"/>contributed to augment it. All the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta</hi>'s Friends wrote to him to <hi>Rome</hi> Letters of Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which had the common Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of that ſort of Epiſtles; and his Relations, who had thought him dead, deſired him to return to <hi>Meſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> to comfort 'em for the Affliction the News of his Death had created in 'em. He began his Journey ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, but had the misfortune to be taken at Sea by a <hi>Majorea</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatier, who having known him for a <hi>Meſſineſe,</hi> delivered him immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to the Duke of <hi>Fernandina,</hi> who was at that time Viceroy of <hi>Sicily.</hi> This generous Duke, who had formerly known the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> and had no ſhare in all the Artifices which his Mother made uſe of for the conſtraining <hi>Yolanda</hi> to accept him for her Husband, was ſo touch'd at his Rival's Misfortune, that very far from executing upon him the Order he had received from <hi>Spain,</hi> to put to death all the <hi>Meſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſes</hi>
                        <pb n="120" facs="tcp:58385:63"/>who ſhould fall into his Hands, he went to ſee him in the Priſon, under pretext of queſtioning him concerning the Affairs of <hi>Meſſina,</hi> and comforted him in Terms very civil and obliging, aſſuring him, that he needed not to be under any fear of his Life, and that he would make known to him, that he had never merited his Hatred, tho' he had been his Rival, adding with a kind of confuſion, That he had but lately known the Violence that had been done <hi>Yolanda</hi> upon his account, and that he would have rather choſen to have loſt her Fortune, than to have married her againſt her will. The Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta,</hi> confuſed to find ſo much Generoſity in a Man whom the Intereſt of his Love had made him look upon as his moſt cruel Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, was at firſt ſomething touch'd by the Duke's obliging Diſcourſes: But repreſenting to himſelf, that a great Courage finds much more ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in a ſuch-like Revenge,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:58385:63"/>than in another more bloody, he fancied it would be a poorneſs of Spirit in him to make ſhameful Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions to his Rival, and made him anſwer after a haughty manner, That it was in vain for him to do himſelf the Honour to ſave his Life, which was not in his power, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſobeying the Orders of <hi>Spain;</hi> That his preſent Circumſtances would make him receive Death as a Favour, having onely ſurvived <hi>Yo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landa</hi> to revenge her, in contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to deliver his Country from the Inſults of the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> and that at preſent, that the <hi>French</hi> were entred into <hi>Meſſina,</hi> he had nothing more to deſire. The Duke of <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandina,</hi> admiring this Generoſity, replied, That he ought to have more reſpectful Sentiments for his Lawful Prince; and then aſſured him, that his Power was not ſo limited, but that he could preſerve his Life, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſobeying the King. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences juſtified that he ſpoke to
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:58385:64"/>him with ſincerity; and he not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſweetned his Impriſonment, by ſeveral little Liberties which he gave him, but he wrote alſo into <hi>Spain,</hi> That he had deferred putting him to death, that ſo the Nobility of <hi>Sicily</hi> might not be wrought up to perfect Deſpair, and to prevent the Cabals which his Relations, whoſe Power was formidable, would have made in the other Cities of the Kingdom, which were already ſufficiently ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered by the Example of <hi>Meſſina;</hi> adding, That he was in hopes uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to employ the Miniſtry of that Priſoner, for the reducing the <hi>Meſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſes</hi> to ſome Accommodation. The Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> fearing the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of this Revolt, abated of its former Rigour, upon the Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy's Remonſtrances, and returned him this Anſwer, That they relied upon his Prudence in that Buſineſs, and that ſince he thought in conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for the good of the preſent State of Affairs, they remitted to
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:58385:64"/>him the Execution of that Prince. But we muſt leave the Prince for ſome time in a Priſon which is not over-rigorous, to go in the mean while and learn Tidings of <hi>Yolanda.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>As ſoon as the perfidious <hi>Trik</hi> had parted with the Prince, he thought of nothing but of glutting his Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, by drawing a conſiderable Sum from the Sale of <hi>Yolanda,</hi> and having carried her to the Port of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> he had her propoſed to the Baſhaw who has the Superin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendence of the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> as one of the moſt Beautiful Perſons in the World. This Baſhaw having ſeen her, was ſatisfied with her Beauty, tho' he could have rather wiſhed ſhe had been perfectly Fair, becauſe the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> has more inclination to love thoſe who are ſo, than all others: Nevertheleſs, he bought her, and put her into the <hi>Seraglio.</hi> So many ſeveral Deſcriptions have been ſeen of that Houſe of Pleaſure of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Emperours, that every
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:58385:65"/>one fancies he is perfectly well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of every Circumſtance of the Place: yet the truth is, few have given an exact Account of it, becauſe that extraordinary care has been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to hinder the Publick, and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally Strangers, from coming to the knowledge of what paſſes therein: But let the Reader be pleaſed to take the following Relation of it, which I have drawn out of Memoires which were given me for authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Seraglio</hi> is a very vaſt Houſe, wherein there is almoſt an infinite number of extraordinary fine Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, all diſtinguiſhed by different Gardens. Theſe Lodgings are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up by the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> by the <hi>Sultana's,</hi> and by ſeveral Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Perſons, who are choſen out of all Nations in the World, without any diſtinction of Birth or of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Beauty alone being required for their admittance Nevertheleſs, they perform a kind of Noviceſhip, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:58385:65"/>they appear before the Eyes of the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> and particular care is taken to teach 'em the <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh</hi> Tongue, in caſe they underſtand it not, that if they have the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of pleaſing his Highneſs, they may be capable of anſwering him, without robbing him of the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Converſation, which is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly what commonly affords moſt delight. They are governed and ſerved by Eunuchs, who for the moſt part have but very little Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance, and treat 'em with a great deal of ſeverity. The firſt Year they enter the <hi>Seraglio</hi> is ſpent in learning divers Exerciſes, and the <hi>Salamelek,</hi> or the Reverence they are taught to make in extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Ceremonies. They are after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards admitted, or ſent back, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as they have Qualities ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to pleaſe the <hi>Grand Seignior;</hi> and the Stories which have run up and down <hi>Europe,</hi> of the Reſiſtance his Highneſs met with in a cruel
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:58385:66"/>Beauty, are ſo far from being true, that never any Lady was introduc'd to the Emperour, until ſhe had made ſolemn Proteſtations that ſhe loved him, and that ſhe would never ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect endeavouring to pleaſe him. During the firſt Year, they are ſhewn every day in a great Hall as many Pourtraicts of the <hi>Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior</hi> as he has Years, each of which repreſents how he was made and clothed the firſt Day of that Year. Thoſe who out of Principles of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, or of Modeſty, reſiſt the Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Tricks of the Eunuchs, who are propoſed to inſpire them with Love for the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> are ſhut up in a kind of Monaſtery conſecrated to <hi>Mahomet,</hi> wherein they obſerve ſeveral Vows, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally that of Chaſtity. And as the number of 'em is very ſmall, they are had in great veneration, the <hi>Turks</hi> calling 'em <hi>The Wives of their Great Prophet.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Yolanda</hi> having been conducted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:58385:66"/>the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> was under extreme Diſquiets, upon the conſideration of her preſent Condition; and tho' the Death of her Lover, and her other Misfortunes, had made her look with indifferency upon all that could happen to her, the fear of the Violences which ſhe imagined would be done her, kept her in continual apprehenſions, until that an <hi>Euro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pean</hi> Eunuch, who was her Maſter in the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Tongue, had ſetled her Mind a little at reſt, by acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her with what was obſerved in the <hi>Seraglio.</hi> He aſſured her, there was no Example of Force ever ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been made uſe of, to conſtrain any Lady to ſatisfie the Deſires of the <hi>Grand Seignior;</hi> adding, with a kind of Complaint, That the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raglio</hi> was but too much filled up with the Cabals of thoſe who court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Favour of the <hi>Sultana's,</hi> or the Protection of the Chief of the Eunuchs, for to inſinuate into the Emperour the Violence of their Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:58385:67"/>and endeavour by ſuch like Artifices to be preferr'd before their Companions. <hi>Yolanda</hi> being inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly diſabuſed of the Terrours which ſhe had framed to her ſelf of the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> applied her ſelf very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to learn the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Tongue, and ſpent the time ſhe did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon her Leſſons, in playing upon Inſtruments, whereof the ſhe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted her ſelf to admiration. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving obſerved ſeveral times, that a young Eunuch eyed her attentive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nay, and ſerved her with more application and reſpect than the others, theſe Diſtinctions began to render her uneaſie, fearing perhaps that this Eunuch might be an Emiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary of the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, that plied about her with ſome Deſign: But her Amazement was much greater, when that one day, being alone in her Chamber, this Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch came in, with his Face all ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in Tears, and told her, That he had for a long while heſitated ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:58385:67"/>to her, out of the ſhame he had to make himſelf known, in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Eſtate he was reduced to, which was a thouſand times worſe to him than Death: Nevertheleſs, what repugnance ſoever he had thereto, the deſire he had to render her Service, by informing her of the Affairs of the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> which he had learnt by an Experience of three years, had prevailed with him over the ſhame of his Condition. <hi>Yolan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> eyed him in the mean while, and had a confuſed Idea of the Face of that Perſon, tho' ſhe was entirely unacquainted with his Voice. The Eunuch perceiving that ſhe could not recal him to mind, and that ſhe was in ſome perplexity, <hi>It is not at all extraordinary that you know me not again,</hi> purſued he, <hi>I am perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that there is a very great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between Don</hi> Auguſtin Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio, Yolanda<hi>'s Lover, and a ſorry Eunuch of the</hi> Seraglio, <hi>and you.</hi> The Tears which trickled from his Eyes
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:58385:68"/>in abundance, hindred hm from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding. At length <hi>Yolanda</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him again for Don <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> tho' ſhe found his Countenance very much changed, and his Voice whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly different, immediately declared her ſelf very joyful to ſee him; and not underſtanding, perhaps, that there was ſo great a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween an Eunuch and another Man, ſhe reproached him with his Deſpair, telling him, That it became him to have more Chriſtian Sentiments, and hope that Heaven would free him out of that Slavery, by procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him the Means of returning in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Sicily. For your part, you may ſtill flatter your ſelf with thoſe Hopes,</hi> replied Don <hi>Auguſtin; and the onely Comfort I have left in my Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, is, to hope that I may perhaps contribute thereto by my Counſels. But for my part, who am only an unhappy Wretch, and have nothing more of a Man than a falſe appearance, it is long ſince I reſolved upon my Courſe of
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:58385:68"/>Life, and have reſigned my ſelf to ſpend my Days in the Employment you ſee me officiate. Yolanda,</hi> ſurpriſed at this Diſcourſe, did imagine that an Eunuch was ſome hideous ſort of thing; but ſhe choſe rather to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in ignorance, than expoſe her ſelf to the hearing an Explication, as would perhaps have wounded her Modeſty. After this firſt Diſcovery, Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> deſired her to tell him. Tidings of the Prince of <hi>Eſcaletta.</hi> This Name having renewed <hi>Yolan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi>'s Grief, ſhe let him know, by a Torrent of Tears, which ſhe could not keep in, that ſomething fatal had hapned to him; and then told him after what manner ſhe believed he was unhappily caſt away. Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> perceived that <hi>Yolanda</hi> was extremely afflicted; the habit he had got of bewailing, made him find her Tears ſo reaſonable, that he had not the power to comfort her, and withdrew without ſaying a Word more: But not being willing too to
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:58385:69"/>abandon her in her Affliction, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Apartment of another Lady, whom he knew to be of a very gay and facetious Humour; he let her know, how he came fro lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Yolanda</hi> in a piteous Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and deſired her to go into her Chamber, to help to diſſipate her doleful melancholy Reflexions. As Ladies love to be obliging, and as Beautiful Perſons have commonly a Complaiſance for one another, (when that the Intereſt of the Jealouſie of their Beauties has not yet changed their Temper) <hi>Zarabey</hi> (ſo was the Lady's Name) went that very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into <hi>Yolanda</hi>'s Chamber, and made uſe of all her good Humour to divert her. <hi>Yolanda</hi> was ſo ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly pleaſed with this generous Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance of <hi>Zarabey,</hi> that ſhe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpended her Grief, to make Returns to her Civilities. Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> coming back a little while after; was very glad to find the Converſation of <hi>Zarabey</hi> had produced the Effect
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:58385:69"/>he had promiſed to himſelf. As he was well acquainted with the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raglio,</hi> and had a great Opinion of <hi>Zarabey,</hi> he counſelled <hi>Yolanda</hi> to contract a Friendſhip with her: and <hi>Yolanda</hi> found her own Inclination ſo diſpoſed to follow his Counſel, that ſhe willingly made all the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Paces for the engaging this Commerce. <hi>Zarabey</hi> was one of thoſe perfect Beauties who have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what is admirable; ſhe was fair, and juſt ſuch a Perſon as was the very Hearts delight of the <hi>Grand Seignior:</hi> Her gay Humour gave new Graces to the Charms which abounded in her Face. She anſwered with ſo much acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement the Teſtimonies of <hi>Yolanda</hi>'s Friendſhip, that in a little while they came to a perfect good Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. The Eunuch, Don <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> contributed very much towards the cementing this Union, by the advantageous Accounts he gave of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> to <hi>Zarabey,</hi> and of <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key</hi>
                        <pb n="134" facs="tcp:58385:70"/>to <hi>Yolanda.</hi> They met almoſt every Hour; and this great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce having inſtill'd into 'em a high eſteem for one another, they lived in the moſt endearing Terms imaginable. The Intereſt which <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabey</hi> took already in her Friend, made her deſirous to learn by what Adventure ſhe was come into the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> being of ſo diſtant a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. <hi>Yolanda,</hi> unwilling to refuſe this Token of the Confidence ſhe had in her, gave her an exact Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of all that had hapned to her, and not having been able to keep in her tears when that ſhe ſpoke to her of the loſs of her Lover, and of the loſs of her Liberty, <hi>Zarabey</hi> ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing highly ſurpriſed to ſee her ſhed Tears, told her very ingenuouſly, That ſhe did not underſtand how ſhe could complain of Evils which had had ſo happy an Iſſue, and had procured her the Means of entring into the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> which is the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Flight of the Ambition of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:58385:70"/>and the greateſt Happineſs that can befal a Perſon of their Sex. <hi>Yolanda,</hi> much more amazed to ſee her have ſuch like Sentiments, than the other had been at her Grief, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired ſhe would tell her by what Circumſtance the Condition of the Slaves of the <hi>Seraglio</hi> ſeemed to her ſo happy. <hi>I perceive,</hi> reparteed <hi>Zarabey, that you have been brought up amongſt the</hi> Barbarians, <hi>ſince that being of a Sex which ſubjects you to the Caprices of Men, who often, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding what Merit ſoever you may have, prefer before you a wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Slave, without Birth or Vertue, and ever confound you with a number of other Women of all Humours, you can ſtill complain of being in the</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raglio, <hi>where we live in vaſt Plenty, and amidſt Delights, without any other Care than that of pleaſing the Emperour of the World, and the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Man of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe. Yolanda</hi> judging by this Diſcourſe of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Condition of the Women of
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:58385:71"/>
                        <hi>Turkey,</hi> where a Husband may have a number of Wives, proportionable to the Eſtate he has to maintain 'em, would needs undeceive <hi>Zarabey,</hi> by giving her to underſtand, that the Circumſtances were not altogether alike in <hi>Europe,</hi> where the Laws are more advantageous to the Ladies, a Man not being allowed to marry more than one Wife, whom he was obliged to conſider as his Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without being permitted to have another while that was living. This ſeemed ſo extraordinary to <hi>Zarabey,</hi> that ſhe was perſuaded <hi>Yolanda</hi> ſought to divert her, and make her ſelf merry, by telling her ſuch like Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, until that Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in, confirmed it to her very ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, and added too, That not onely the Men of his Country had but one Wife, but that it often hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned too, that that Woman was the Miſtreſs of ſeveral Men, without her Husband's daring in any wiſe to complain.</p>
                     <pb n="137" facs="tcp:58385:71"/>
                     <p> Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> had been ſo ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Relation which <hi>Yolanda</hi> had given her of what had hapned to her in <hi>Spain,</hi> that <hi>Zarabey</hi> had an extreme Curioſity to learn from him himſelf the Sequel of his Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes. <hi>Yolanda</hi> had in vain deſired it of him ſeveral times; he had ſtill excuſed himſelf, not daring to expoſe himſelf to the Confuſion he was afraid of receiving by a Relation whoſe end was ſo Tragical to him. However, thoſe two Beautiful Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons having deſired him very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, what averſion ſoever his Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances gave him for Women, the Conſideration he had for <hi>Yolanda</hi> and for <hi>Zarabey</hi> prevailed over all his other Motions; and being preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed beyond denial, he valued to 'em this Account as the ſtrongeſt Proof he could give 'em of his Complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance: and after having acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 'em with all that had befallen him until his going out of <hi>Spain, You know,</hi> ſaid he, addreſſing his
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:58385:72"/>Speech to <hi>Yolanda, that the Queen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing highly offended at my Audaciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, was reſolved to inflict on me an exemplary Puniſhment; but was part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diverted from it by the earneſt Supplications of my Friends, who could not however hinder my being ſent back into</hi> Sicily, <hi>with order to him who had the Care to conduct me, to detain me a Month in the Caſtle of</hi> S. Sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veur, <hi>and to ſhew me there in the Garb and Habit which had diſguiſed me in the Palace, for to puniſh me in the very thing wherein my Crime con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted. They made me embarque at</hi> Barcelona, <hi>in a Merchants Ship, freighted with ſeveral Goods belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to</hi> Genoueſes. <hi>Hardly were we part of the way, but that we were at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taqued with a violent Tempeſt, which caſt us upon the Coaſts of</hi> Barbary. <hi>A</hi> Turkiſh Corſair <hi>which ſcoured that Sea having diſcovered us, and percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſad pickle the Storm had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced us to, attacked our Ship when half in pieces, and eaſily rendred him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:58385:72"/>Maſter of it. The Severity where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with our Conquerour treated at firſt ſeveral Perſons of our Ship, whom he put into Chains, making me fear the like Treatment, determined me not to undeceive him of the Errour my Garb might lead him in, hoping he would have the more reſpect for my Perſon. I ſucceeded but too well in this Deſign: The Corſair having found me very much to his mind, treated me with a great deal of Civility, and inſenſibly let me know I had made ſome impreſſion upon his Heart. Short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after he ſpoke to me of his Paſſion, as a great Happineſs for me, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring ſtill to perſuade me that he was my Slave, tho' by the Right of War I was his. My Anſwer let him know, that I was very far from making Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns to all theſe Addreſſes. But this was ſo far from making him ceaſe his Purſuit, his Paſſion augmented by my Reſiſtances; and finding my ſelf preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by this furious Man, I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to free him out of the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:58385:73"/>my Diſguiſe had plunged him in, by letting him know what I was. The Perſons who accompanied me, having confirmed to him my Words, I thought I ſhould have been freed from his Perſecutions; but the knowledge here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of did put him in that rage againſt me that he would needs immediately have me puniſhed by fifty Blows of a Cudgel, which he ordered ſhould be given me immediately upon the Soals of my Feet, and which I was onely ſaved from by the arrival of an Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer from the Captain</hi> Baſhaw, <hi>or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral, who having heard talk of the Misfortune of our Ship, had ſent this Officer to receive the Share which was due to him by his Charge over all the Prizes, before they had embezelled what was moſt precious, as often hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens. The</hi> Baſhaw<hi>'s Envoy, after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving viſited all things with all poſſible exactneſs, choſe me, with two other Perſons, for his Maſters Share. This the</hi> Corſair <hi>did not oppoſe, ſeeing that in conſideration of my pretended Sex,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:58385:73"/>and of my good Meen, this Officer took me for a conſiderable Prize: He ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs pretended to complain of his being robbed of the beſt of his Prize, and deſired him that he would at leaſt leave the two others who were to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company me; which was granted him at length. I ſhall not amuſe you with the impertinent Particulars of my Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, nor with the Satisfaction which my Guide took in carrying me along. He conducted me to</hi> Conſtantinople, <hi>and preſented me to the Captain</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw. <hi>This</hi> Turk, <hi>who under the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of a great deal of Probity, concealed the moſt Cruel of all Men, ſeemed to be very well ſatisfied with me: He told me in the</hi> Lingua Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, (<hi>which is a Language mixed with</hi> Italian, <hi>and very eaſie to underſtand) That he eaſily perceived I was a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Quality, and that I might aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure my ſelf he would diſtinguiſh me from his other Slaves. I made him no other Anſwer than by a Curt'ſie; and he then led me into an Apartment,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:58385:74"/>where the Slaves of my new Maſter received me with great Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Good-will, and with much more Humanity than I could have hoped for from a Nation that had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to me ſo Barbarous. The next day after my arrival, he had me clothed in</hi> Turkiſh <hi>Garments, which were extreme neat, but not rich in the leaſt. The</hi> Baſhaw <hi>would needs I ſhould ſerve him that day at Dinner; He liked me ſo well in that Garb, that I began to be afraid, by the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction he let me know he took in me, that ſome new Diſaſter would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal me. I was firſt thinking to prevent him, and had twenty times the Deſign of laying my ſelf at his Feet, for to declare to him what I was, before that my Diſguiſe had thrown me into new Perplexities; but I was ſtill divert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from it by the remembrance of the</hi> Corſairs <hi>Menaces, when I made to him the like Confeſſion. This unhappy Reflection created in me ſuch a dread, that I reſolved to continue in my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe.
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:58385:74"/>The</hi> Baſhaw <hi>treated me after ſuch a manner, as confirmed me in my apprehenſion; but I had not place left to doubt of my Misfortune, when that calling for me one day, he told me, how he had a great Eſteem for me, nay, and that he found himſelf diſpoſed to love me; That it was my part to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, by my Complaiſance and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for his Perſon, what my good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune had begun. The Trouble which appeared in my Looks after this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, having quickly let him know that this rendred me uneaſie, he continued ſpeaking to me, and told me, That I needed not to ſtand in fear of any Violence from him, not being of the Humour of other</hi> Patrons, <hi>who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to by main Force what is refus'd 'em out of Kindneſs; That very far from having the thought of making uſe of the Authority he had over me as his Slave, he was ſo nice in Love, he would be convinced I had an Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for him, before he could reſolve upon loving me. This laſt Diſcourſe
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:58385:75"/>having encouraged me again, he went away without ſtaying for my Anſwer, and ſpent ſeveral days without ſaying to me a word more. His Silence made me judge he had always ſpoke to me with ſincerity, until that having preſented me with a very rich Robe, and very different from that of the other Slaves, he told me, That he made me that Preſent, to engage me to pleaſe him out of Acknowledgement, ſince I could not do it out of Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I made him anſwer, That I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied much upon his Generoſity, and that I was perſuaded he would not force me to do any thing that was contrary to my Religion and my Duty.</hi> Never fear it, <hi>replied he to me,</hi> my Word is inviolable; I have given it you, and that is ſufficient. <hi>I was ſo perſuaded of the great Generoſity of my</hi> Baſhaw, <hi>that I began to breathe, and find my Condition leſs unhappy: However, a modeſt Air which I affected, for the better maintaining my Perſonage, and the application I had to acquit my ſelf
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:58385:75"/>of ſuch thing as were committed to my Care, perfectly inflamed him. The little diſpoſition he ſaw me have to love him, rendred him very pettiſh; and I perceived that his Wives, who had all imaginable Complaiſance for him, endeavoured to divert him all in vain. One of thoſe whom he loved moſt, called</hi> Salama, <hi>having perceived by his Sighs that he had ſome Paſſion in his Head, knew ſo well how to make uſe of the good Opinion the</hi> Baſhaw <hi>had of her, that he owned to her at length, that I had inſpired him with Love. As the</hi> Turkiſh <hi>Women are accuſtomed to ſuch like Infidelities, and that they are not ſo much as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to ſhew the leaſt Jealouſie, for fear of irritating their Husbands, by oppoſing what they deſire,</hi> Salama <hi>had not the leaſt thought of blaming him. On the contrary, ſhe commended him in having made ſo good a choice, and promiſed him to ſpeak to me in his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, for the letting me know of what conſequence it was to me to lay hold on
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:58385:76"/>my good Fortune. The</hi> Baſhaw <hi>very much ſatisfied with an Offer which ſo highly flattered his Deſires, deſired her to go about it with all poſſible ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, aſſuring her ſhe could not give him a more ſenſible Token of her Love.</hi> Salama <hi>called me into the Garden, where after having cajolled and careſſed me very highly, ſhe ſpoke to me of the</hi> Baſhaw<hi>'s Paſſions, of his Merit, and of all the great Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges I might hope for by making Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns thereto. I own, that having been brought up in</hi> Europe, <hi>where the Women are ſo nice upon this Matter, I was amazed to ſee with what Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence</hi> Salama <hi>endeavoured to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade me to love her Husband; which made me ſuſpect that her Jealouſie had inſpired her to make uſe of this Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the diſcovering my Sentiments. I made her anſwer, That I thought the</hi> Baſhaw <hi>a Man of too good a Taſte, and too much Senſe, having ſo lovely a Wife as ſhe, to entertain any thoughts of an unfortunate Slave.</hi> I perceive,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:58385:76"/>
                        <hi>replied</hi> Salama, that you are afraid of diſpleaſing me, and that you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps apprehend that I ſhould trepan you; but that you may no longer have that thought, know, that the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> himſelf made known to me the Paſſion he has for you; and as I onely ſeek to ſatisfie him, I have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken upon me to ſpare him the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your Reſiſtance would have cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>attd in him. You are a Perſon of too much Reaſon, to bring ſo Great a Man into Deſpair, out of a Delica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy which commonly proceeds onely from a falſe Principle of Modeſty, wedded to our Sex, which ought never to be put in practice, but when it ſerves to make Men ſet the greater Value upon us. <hi>I knew by ſo free a Diſcourſe the Sentiments which the</hi> Turks <hi>infuſe into Women upon the Point of Vertue, for the ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring 'em the more ſubmiſſive to their Wills.</hi> Salama <hi>did not preſs me any further; but two days after, having had me called into the ſame Garden,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:58385:77"/>ſhe made me new Inſtances, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to me more ſtrongly than the firſt time, how much it did import me to receive a Fortune, which ſo many others wiſh for to no purpoſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Tho'</hi> Salama <hi>was a perfect Beauty, and that the</hi> Baſhaw <hi>diſtinguiſh'd her from all his Wives; as ſhe alone could not fulfil his Deſires, ſhe complied like a Woman of Senſe with his Inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and rendring her ſelf complaiſant to all his Paſſions, ſhe thereby preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved an Empire which her Beauty alone could not have given her. Theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons engaged her to ſolicit me with ſo much zeal and fervency, as produced in me Motions very different from thoſe ſhe meant to inſpire. I began to have for</hi> Salama <hi>what ſhe endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to inſtil into me for her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. She exaggerated to me the</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw<hi>'s Love in ſuch touching, melting Terms, that I could not defend my ſelf againſt all the Charms which ſhe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſplayed in that moment for to perſuade me: Whereupon I determined to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:58385:77"/>her with what I was, without being able to unravel whether I did it to avoid falling into the Inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies whereof I have already ſpoken, or out of hopes of drawing ſome Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage from the Diſcovery I made her. Never was Perſon more ſurpris'd than</hi> Salama <hi>ſeemed to be, at her hearing ſo extraordinary a piece of News. She was for ſome time without making me any Anſwer, and pretending not to believe what I had told her, I made uſe of her affected Ignorance, and took Liberties with her which are allowed of in Perſons of the ſame Sex. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſucceeded in this Trial, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving to find in her all the Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence I could deſire, whether ſhe found in me ſomething ſhe liked, or that ſhe was tempted by the eaſineſs of a Commerce which could never be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected, ſhe made tender Returns to my Tranſports, and I nicked the Occaſion.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Now our whole thoughts were onely how to keep the</hi> Baſhaw <hi>in his Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and ſeek the Means of ſeeing
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:58385:78"/>one another often. The Pretext ſhe took to ſpeak to me in favour of her Husband, furniſhed her with Occaſions enough; yet ſhe was now and then forced to give Reaſons for my Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, ſometimes making my Modeſty the Impediment, and at others my bad Health. We amuſed the</hi> Baſhaw <hi>for above three Months with ſuch like Artifices, and I began to be pretty well ſatisfied with my Captivity, by the Care</hi> Salama <hi>took to ſweeten it, and by the Promiſe ſhe made me, That as ſoon as the</hi> Baſhaw <hi>was put to Sea for to command the Ships which were to depart in a ſhort time for</hi> Meccha, <hi>ſhe would find the means of flying away with me into my own Country.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Full of theſe Hopes, I redoubled my Tranſports and Addreſſes to</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lama; <hi>when that the</hi> Baſhaw, <hi>impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient in his Love, would needs inquire himſelf into what he was to hope from me; and ſuſpecting perhaps his Wife did not uſe her Efforts to prevail with me to comply with his Deſires, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:58385:78"/>to watch us narrowly. The moſt uſual Place of our Converſations was a</hi> Grotto <hi>at the end of a Garden, whither People could not come without being perceived by thoſe who were in it. The <hi>Baſhaw</hi> having ſtole cunningly into that Place, hid himſelf there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that we came. The Impatience of ſeeing one another without Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, did not allow us to take any long Walk. As ſoon as we were got into that</hi> Grotto, <hi>we abandoned our ſelves to our Love with all the Confidence of two Lovers, who think they have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to fear; and the</hi> Baſhaw <hi>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed us in a Condition as cleared all Doubts of what I was, and laid open the Treachery of his Wife. His Rage inſpired him forthwith with what Courſe he was to take; and having called for a Slave whom he knew pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for executing the Deſign which his Jealouſie ſuggeſted to him, he rendred me uncapable of ever making any one jealous for the future.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Tears which the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:58385:79"/>of ſo barbarous an Action drew from poor Don <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled his Voice, and hindred him from being able to continue. What Compaſſion ſoever ſo piteous a Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry did create in <hi>Yolanda</hi> and <hi>Zara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey,</hi> they could not refuſe their Sex feeling a Contempt for Don <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> nor laughing at the State this cruel Accident had reduced that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Perſon to. The Diſorder he was in, hindred him from perceiving it; and they were ſo earneſt with him to tell 'em the Deſtiny of <hi>Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> that he was obliged to continue his Diſcourſe in theſe Terms.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The unfortunate</hi> Salama, <hi>who was forced by her Husband to aſſiſt at the execution of his Orders, reſolved to prevent the Reproaches and Cruelties of that</hi> Barbarian, <hi>by ſeiſing a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyard which the</hi> Baſhaw <hi>wore by his Side, with which ſhe endeavoured to kill her ſelf; but her Hand having too weakly ſeconded her deſpair, ſhe onely gave her ſelf a ſlight Wound;
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:58385:79"/>and the</hi> Baſhaw <hi>ſurpriſed at her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, had her carried away. I was for above eight days in hopes Death would deliver me from my Ignominy; however, my Youth, and the Care that was taken to pleaſe the</hi> Baſhaw, <hi>who had recommended that nothing ſhould be ſpared for my Health and Recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry (perhaps out of the pleaſure he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to himſelf in inſulting over my Misfortune) contributed ſo much to my Cure, that in a ſhort time I was in good Health, notwithſtanding the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret I had to live. My Deſpair did not hinder me from intereſſing my ſelf in the Fortune of</hi> Salama, <hi>and I had a kind of Conſolation to learn, that the</hi> Baſhaw, <hi>touch'd with her Repentance, and compaſſionating the Weakneſs of her Sex, had pardoned her at length.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The</hi> Baſhaw <hi>having bethought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of diverting the</hi> Grand Vizier <hi>by the Account of his Cruelties and my Misfortunes, this Miniſter had the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity to ſee me; and having found in me all the Lines and Features of
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:58385:80"/>that Beauty which had been ſo fatal to me, he made known to the</hi> Baſhaw <hi>that the</hi> Grand Seignior <hi>would be glad to hear this Story, and adviſed him to preſent me to his Highneſs, for to ſerve him in the</hi> Seraglio, <hi>which the</hi> Baſhaw <hi>promiſed him to do in my preſence; nay, and I looked upon this Employment as a Bleſſing, ſince it would free me from the ſight of my Executioner. But before I had that feeble Comfort, he would needs give a new Regale to his Revenge, having called me to ſerve him at Supper in my Garb of an Eunuch. I was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely ſurpriſed to ſee</hi> Salama, <hi>who was eating with him, and diverted him with a very gay and facetious Converſation. The pleaſure which I obſerved ſhe took in doing it, confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to me what I had often heard ſay of the Levity of Perſons of her Sex, who are eaſily comforted for the loſs of thoſe whom they have loved with moſt Affection. But when that, of her own Motion, I ſaw that s;he excited the</hi>
                        <pb n="155" facs="tcp:58385:80"/>Baſhaw <hi>to look upon me, and to laugh, I perceived I had been all my Life long miſtaken in the good Opinion I had had of the feigned tenderneſs of ſuch like Perſons: For my State was ſo far from raiſing her Compaſſion, that ſhe inſulted over me with ſeveral Railleries, The</hi> Baſhaw <hi>was ſo ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with her Complaiſance, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired her to relate to him what Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces I had made uſe of to ſeduce her. She obeyed him without repugnance, and affected ſo much Contempt for me, that I cannot remember you are of the Sex of that perfidious Perſon, without having ſome reſentment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This laſt Circumſtance cauſed ſo much Grief in Don <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> that he went away in haſte, without liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the Prayers of <hi>Yolanda</hi> and of <hi>Zarabey,</hi> who would have ſtill detained him.</p>
                     <p>Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> was hardly gone out, when that a Black Eunuch came in, to give thoſe two beautiful
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:58385:81"/>Perſons notice to be at a <hi>Sarao,</hi> or Dance, which was held in the Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Chief of the Eunuchs. <hi>Yolanda,</hi> who was no longer ſenſible to Pleaſures, would willingly have diſpenſed her ſelf from going thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but ſhe had the Complaiſance of accompanying <hi>Zarabey,</hi> who lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thoſe Divertiſements, and who beſides was overjoyed to be at thoſe kind of Aſſemblies, to obſerve if there was any Lady who could diſpute with her the Advantages wherewith ſhe was ſo liberally gift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Nature. She came alſo away from thence very well ſatisfied, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving either had the Happineſs or Cunning to gain a rich Necklace of Pearl, which was the Reward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for her who ſhould acquit her ſelf of that Dance with the beſt Grace. <hi>Yolanda</hi> was none of the laſt to congratulate her upon this Occaſion; and as ſhe had not any deſign to pleaſe in the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> ſhe was very glad to ſee that her Friend
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:58385:81"/>diſtinguiſhed her ſelf. They lived in a ſtrict Union; and Don <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> contrary to the Cuſtom of other Eunuchs, had ſo much Complaiſance for 'em, that he facilitated to 'em the means of ſeeing and entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another very often, tho' that theſe Converſations be not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd 'em but certain Days of the Week. <hi>Yolanda</hi> had ſo great an Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection for <hi>Zarabey,</hi> as made her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to be acquainted with her Circumſtances, of which ſhe one day took occaſion to ſpeak to her, and deſired her to acquaint her how ſhe came into the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> and if her Relations had given their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thereto, or if ſhe had been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by violence from their Houſe. <hi>I ſhould pardon any other Perſon ſo groſs an Errour,</hi> interrupted <hi>Zara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey,</hi> laughing; <hi>but you who have ſo much Wit, may eaſily believe, that there be ſuch unjuſt Parents as to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Happineſs of their Children, when that they are choſen to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:58385:82"/>the</hi> Seraglio. <hi>I did not remember,</hi> replied <hi>Yolanda, that you had already called me</hi> Barbarian <hi>in the like Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation; nay, I will own, ſince you will needs have it ſo, that I was in the wrong, to ask you a Queſtion ſo fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign to good ſenſe; but in revenge no longer defer acquainting me by what extraordinary good luck you have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to a Felicity which you ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prize. The Eunuch, Don</hi> Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin, <hi>has already made me the ſame Requeſt,</hi> ſaid <hi>Zarabey; I'll paſs my word to ſatisfie your Curioſity, as ſoon as we are all together.</hi> Happily Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> came in in that very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and <hi>Zarabey</hi> began her Story in this manner.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Name of my Grandfather has made ſo much noiſe in the Eaſt, that I may without ſhame own to you my Extraction, if the laſt Action he did, in renouncing our Great Prophet, had not defaced all his Glory. He was an</hi> European, <hi>and of</hi> Chriſtian <hi>Race: Nevertheleſs, he had been brought up
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:58385:82"/>at the</hi> Port, <hi>and with ſo much happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that he had merited the Eſteem of the</hi> Grand Seignior, <hi>who gave him Teſtimonies thereof in all Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, The Worth and Valour he had ſhew'd in ſeveral Employments he was truſted with, had cauſed his Birth to be forgotten: He was treated as if he had been born a</hi> Muſſulman, <hi>and enjoyed the ſame Privileges with thoſe who had that Advantage. I will not give you here the Particulars of the Life of that Great Man, all the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of his Time ſpeak thereof ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently: It is enough, I tell you, that after having ſpent forty years in the Emperour's Service, he had the Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſo uſual to moſt Men, and wiſh'd to ſee again his Native Country. Yet as he was much above the common rate of Perſons, I can hardly believe he ſuffered himſelf to be led away by ſuch ordinary Sentiments; and it is much more probable, that a Chriſtian Slave whom he loved paſſionately in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clenſion of his Age, had the Art to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:58385:83"/>a Deſire he had always had, of returning into the Religion of his Forefathers, and determined him by her Importunities to a ſhameful Flight: For having diſpos'd his Affairs with great ſecreſie, he fitted out two good Ships, and after having given part of his Riches to one of his Wives whom he had ever loved, he embarqued with that unhappy Slave, upon I know not what pretext. A Rumour ran a long while after, that he was entred into a Port of the Chriſtians: This was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed from ſo many ſeveral Places, that the Truth of it was no longer doubted of. You may judge with what ſurpriſe his Wives heard theſe ſad Tydings, and principally ſhe whom he had ever diſtinguiſhed, who expected his Return with Impatience, which will be eaſie for you to imagine, when you ſhall know, that ſhe proved with Child, (and from that Great Belly came my Father.) She repreſented to her ſelf every moment the Joy her Husband would receive, by learning,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:58385:83"/>that at a time when he was almoſt out of hopes of having Children, ſhe was upon the point, perhaps, of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him a Succeſſor, who might one day maintain the Reputation of his Name, ſo noted in the</hi> Ottoman <hi>Empire. But that which ought to have proved her Joy, did onely ſerve to make her the more dolefully ſenſible of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, or to ſay rather, the loſs of her Husband. This grieved her to ſuch a degree, that ſhe was brought to Bed before her time. People talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed variouſly of my Grandfathers De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture: His Friends, who were very numerous, having an abhorrence of an Action ſo unworthy that Great Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, took care to give out he had been take by the Gallies of</hi> Malta: <hi>And as the Truth is never well known of what paſſes at Sea, this Artifice, which gave People occaſion to doubt whether his Abſence was voluntary, has rendred his Memory leſs odious: And his Son, or my Father, if you pleaſe, who in a tender Age was already ſtrong and
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:58385:84"/>robuſt, was brought up at the</hi> Grand Seignior<hi>'s Court. People were inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly ſpeaking to him of the Glory which his Father had acquired; and before he was at an Age of going to the War, he was already full of that noble Boldneſs ſo natural to Great Warriors. As ſoon as he was allowed to be in Occaſions wherein he could ſhew his Courage, he gained the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of all thoſe who ſaw him fight. As I do not deſign to give you here his Hiſtory, I'll content my ſelf with telling you, That after having had conſiderable Advantages over the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the</hi> Grand Seignior, <hi>Love, that Tyrant, which particularly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies it ſelf to the ſubduing of Great Men, triumphed over him in his turn: He ſaw my Mother at his paſſing through</hi> Adrianople; <hi>ſhe was a</hi> Geor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian, <hi>and one of the moſt beautiful Perſons of the World. He liked her ſo extremely well, that he made his Addreſſes to her, and reſolved to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry her. I will not give you an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:58385:84"/>of the Circumſtances of their Amours, tho' attended with very ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Particularities. At length, after abundance of Difficulties, which he van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed by his Perſeverance, his Love was rewarded, and you ſee in me the Fruit of the firſt Year of their Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age. The</hi> Perſians <hi>having at that time brought on foot a numerous Army, which ſeem'd to menace all the</hi> Ottoman <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, my Father was one of the firſt on the March for the oppoſing their unjuſt Deſigns, having ever before his Eyes the Examples of his Father. He had the misfortune to be kill'd in endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to make appear that he was the Worthy Son of the Famous</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw Cigala. <hi>Zarabey</hi> had no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er named the <hi>Baſhaw Cigala,</hi> than that ſhe obſerved a great change in the Faces of thoſe who heard her; but particularly in that of <hi>Yolanda,</hi> who perceiving by the Relation ſhe had newly heard, that <hi>Zarabey</hi> was of her Family, embraced her, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving her time to continue.</p>
                     <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
